<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A second parcel of obiections against the taking of the engagement answered, or, The doubts which som godlie ministers in som neighbor counties entertained upon that subject as they were proposed in several letters to, and resolved by J.D. : whereunto is occasionably annexed a discoverie of the weakness of the plea of the Cheshire and Lancashire ministers for non-subscribing.</title>
            <author>Dury, John, 1596-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 232 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37087</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12277266</idno>
  <idno type="VID">58502</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240970556</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2887</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11448</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12277266</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37087)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58502)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 625:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A second parcel of obiections against the taking of the engagement answered, or, The doubts which som godlie ministers in som neighbor counties entertained upon that subject as they were proposed in several letters to, and resolved by J.D. : whereunto is occasionably annexed a discoverie of the weakness of the plea of the Cheshire and Lancashire ministers for non-subscribing.</title>
                  <author>Dury, John, 1596-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 106 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Will. Du-Gard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 106.</note>
                  <note>Each of the author's letters signed: John Durie.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58502:1"/>
            <p>A second Parcel of OBIECTIONS Against the taking of the ENGAGEMENT ANSWERED.</p>
            <p>Or the doubts which som godlie Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters in som neighbor Counties entertained upon that Subject; as they were proposed in several Letters to, and resolved by <hi>J. D.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereunto is occasionably annexed a discoverie of the weakness of the Plea of the <hi>Cheshire</hi> and <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cashire</hi> Ministers for non-subscribing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Will. Du. Gard.</hi> 1650.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:58502:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58502:2"/>
            <head>A second Parcel of OBIECTIONS against the taking of the ENGAGEMENT answered; Or, the doubts which som godlie Ministers in som neighbor Counties en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained upon that subject, as they were proposed in several Letters to, and resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by <hi>J. D.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="letter">
               <head>The first Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Reverend Sir!</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He scope of your late writings seem's to bee the giving of satisfaction to such as are scrupulous about the new Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Give mee leav (beeing embold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thereunto by your ingenious invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>p.</hi> 29. of your <hi>Re-prop.</hi>) to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you with the thoughts of divers godlie Ministers (whose names you may have if need bee) touching your two last pieces: and to shew you wherein they remain unsatisfied. Only let mee premise thus much, and speak it as in the sight of God; that although my acquaintance hath been but little with you (beeing once only in your companie with Dr. <hi>Wells</hi>) yet I have alwaie highly honored you in my heart, since I had any knowledg of you;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58502:3"/> and have often said to my friends, That if I would rest upon anie man's judgment living, (at lest in points of this nature) it should bee upon yours: so deeply was I possessed with the persua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion both of your abilitie and integritie. And for those, whose thoughts I represent to you, I may truly saize of them, they are such as are led into their doubtings by no design, but the design of keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a good conscience; and that the tie of conscience arising from <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>gements, whereby they have tied themselvs to God, is the principal (if not onlie) thing that make's them tender this waie. You may therefore pleas to take notice:</p>
               <p n="1">1. They think that the less self-confidence, and abounding in our sens, bee used in things of so doubtful a nature, the more agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able it is to the rule of love, and the more safe will our proceedings bee therein.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They think that in your whole discours on this subject, you take that <hi>pro concesso</hi> (and make it the chief basis and bottom of all your argumentation) namely, That the continuance of King and Lords is inconsistent with <hi>Salus Populi;</hi> (whereto it's wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly granted other things must give place): but this is the thing altogether in question, as was otherwise determined by the major part of the Commons (when the Hous was full and free) who are our onelie competent judges in things of this nature.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They think it a sentence scarcely agreeable to the rule of charitie and Christian compassion, that those who are afraid to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage this waie (though they engage to live quietly, and obeie in law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful things) should have no protection or other benefit of law (as you seem to saie <hi>p.</hi> 22. of your <hi>Considerations</hi>) since, wherein is true tenderness of conscience, if it bee not to bee tender in those things wherein wee have to do with God, and that in the most sacred and solemn manner, <hi>viz.</hi> by Oaths and Covenants.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whereas you saie in your <hi>Re-prop. p.</hi> 12. that there is no difference at all betwixt the things which the proposers themselvs mention to bee the dutie of Subjects to their superiors, and the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scriptions required by present Autoritie; And yet <hi>p.</hi> 15.you saie wee mean to declare by our subscriptions our approbation of, our ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying consent unto, and our obligation towards the present Esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishment, (which are the principal things that the proposers scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple at, as appear's <hi>Sect.</hi> 39; And whereas your self would not have
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58502:3"/> it so much as questioned how far it doth implie an approbation of the present establishment, a ratifying consent thereto, and an obligation to act to the strengthning and promoting of it; and yet by subscri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing you declare your approbation of it; they cannot see how these things are clear from contradiction and crossing one another.</p>
               <p n="5">5. They account it an hard censure by you, to saie that those whom nothing can satisfie in their doubts, but a clear declaration made either by the Supreme Power, or by themselves, to bee such as have no sinceritie in them, (pag. 20. of your <hi>Repropos.</hi>) since wee cannot go too clearly and surely to work in acquitting our selvs from the guilt arising from the violation of such oaths and promises as wee have made to God.</p>
               <p n="6">6. They think it no less violation of the rule of charitie, for you to saie of the proposers (though altogether unknown to them) That in their Proposals they have covered a State business and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick design with a Ministerial cloak, <hi>p.</hi> 29. (where there seem's to bee a mixture of som bitterness) then if the proposers should saie of you, that you have put forth your late Papers to pleas a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing partie. And if there bee a libertie to censure each other in this sort, whose integritie shall bee left untouched and unviolated?</p>
               <p n="7">7. They acknowledg that to bee very true, which you speak <hi>p.</hi> 21. and that even good men are too subject to admit of self-mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in their best actions. But they see no reason to think that your self should bee so strong as not to bee at som times subject to the like weakness: If you bee, then you know it is the dutie of the strong to <hi>bear with the infirmities of the weak:</hi> and the propertie of love, rather to cover and conceal them, then to laie them open to their shame, when so manie are readie to rejoice in it.</p>
               <p>To conclude, they are much afraid that the late writings on this subject, have not a little exasperated the higher Powers, and height<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the heat of their indignation against manie that are truly godlie (both Ministers and People that are tender this waie) by increasing unjust jealousies in their minds towards them, and making things ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in a wors shape then needed, and so have made the gap greater and breach wider, which had far more need to have been closed and cured. It is conceived, that you can very hardly prove those things which you suggest against the proposers, and therefore (as your self saie) in doubtful things love should judg the best: And therefore
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58502:4"/> it had been a far better office both of love to your brethren, yea, and of fidelitie to Superiors, rather to have cast on water, then to have added fewel to the flame: autoritie beeing alwaies apt enough to take high offence at such, who in all things agree not with it.</p>
               <p>Sir, you cannot but know that the generalitie of the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> have the same sense of this new Engagement with those that scruple it in <hi>England:</hi> whose judgment is not to bee sleighted. Neither is there reason for anie to bee carried on with such confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in the mainteining of it, as to censure those who are doubtful. You cannot but know that in doubtful things, by reason of the diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie of apprehensions, there will bee likewise a differing latitude in men's consciences (even in the consciences of such as are truly pious and most sincerely conscientious) so as those things which will sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie one, will not satisfie another that desire's satisfaction (as it hath been heretofore between the non-conformists and conformists, (though both godlie) and is still between the Independents and Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians) so that in publick subscriptions it hath been thought needful things should bee as clear as the morning light. That there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore such who desire a clear satisfaction in such a business as this, that is involved with such difficulties, and perplexed with so manie oaths and pre-engagements, should bee censured for unsinceritie; is thought verie little agreeing with the rule of love and equitie.</p>
               <p>It is therefore in all earnestness and loving humilitie desired of you, that you would laie no more load on such who already are even sinking under the burden of manie doubts and perplexities, nor give anie occasion to the hand of Autoritie to lie heavier upon them then heretofore; but rather that you would bestow som of your strength in dealing with Superiors as well as inferiors: and that in these respects:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becaus it is in their power (by not pressing) to eas manie that want power to eas themselvs by untying the knots that pinch them: and it is no small charitie, to yield eas to a tired, troubled conscience.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It will bee their safetie and prosperitie not to laie heavie bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens on the consciences of such as desire to keep a good conscience: such as have alwaie been their fastest friends, and constant interces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors at the Throne of Grace. A blow from a friend is far more grievous, then what come's from an enemie.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:58502:4"/> 3. It will bee very agreeable to those manie promises and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessions they have made to the whole Kingdom, touching their great care to use tender consciences tenderly. When the Prelatical yoke was broken, there was great hopes wee should have been troubled with no more yokes of the like nature.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It's conceived, that now you have a price in your hands, (by reason you have ingratiated your self with the higher Powers by the manie good offices you have don for them) you have opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie likewise to do som good offices for God's people, which they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire you maie have a heart to improve.</p>
               <p>Blessed is hee that considereth or judgeth wisely of the poor (as the <hi>Geneva</hi> translation read's it) <hi>Psal.</hi> 41. 1. You know who those poor ones are, even such as manie are, who are now strugling in their thoughts about the lawfulness of this now Engagement, and not able to finde out a satisfying resolution.</p>
               <p>Thus I have been bold to commend the thoughts of my friends, together with my own thoughts, unto you, which I hope you will accept with that christian candor and meekness, which heretofore hath shined forth in all your carriages. If it pleas you to vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe anie answer, though but in three lines, I shall take it as a true testimonie of your great humilitie and integritie. Thus desiring our good God still to make you a happie reconciler and peacemaker, I resign you to his mercie.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours in all christian love<lb/> and service.</signed>
                  <lb/>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>This ninth of</hi>
                        <lb/> Febr. 1649.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="answer">
               <head>The Answer to the first Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Reverend Sir!</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOur Letter dated <hi>Febr.</hi> 9. I received not till <hi>Febr.</hi> 16. on saturdaie about noon, and I willingly confess my self really beholding to you for the ingenuitie and freedom which you use towards mee in it, and wish that God would put it in the heart of everie one of my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren that find themselves grieved at anie thing which they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58502:5"/> finde in me, to do as you have don. For I hope that God will never suffer mee to neglect anie admonition which shall bee given mee by anie, without a due reflection upon my self to examine my spirit in his sight, by the light which it bring's with it, or without a sollicitous care to give just sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to everie one, whom I may see upon discoverie that I have offended through weakness: for hee was an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle that said, <hi>In manie things wee offend all,</hi> Jam. 3. (not excluding himself) and added, <hi>If anie man offend not in a word, hee is a perfect man:</hi> I am not conscious to my self of anie conceit of perfection in anie thing which I have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined; therefore I shall willingly take notice of the first rule which you laie down, <hi>That the less self-confidence and abounding in our sens wee use in things of a doubtfull nature, the more agreeable our waie will bee to the rule of love; and the more safe will our proceedings bee.</hi> By this rule I shall heartily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to bee judged; and if I have failed by beeing too confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in anie thing, my heart doth much deceiv mee, if I shall ever bee ashamed to confess a fault, if made known unto mee. I shall therefore desire to know the passages wherein self-confidence doth appear, that I may bee hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for them, and rectifie them upon a further examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my heart.</p>
               <p>Your second point of admonition is, <hi>That I take that</hi> pro confesso <hi>which is in question; and that I make that which is not granted to bee the basis and bottom of all my argumentation.</hi> Which if I do, I confess I am out of the waie. But truly, by what you represent, it doth not yet appear to mee that I have don so: for you saie that I have pre-supposed this as the basis of all my argumentation, namely, <hi>That the continuance of K. and Lords is inc<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>sistent with</hi> Salus Populi: which to my best understanding o<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y self in what I have said or meant to saie, I neither have said, nor intended to saie; and I would bee beholden to you, or those other brethren who make that observation, to let mee see the ground of that asserti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in anie thing which I have said. For I will clearly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess, that I do not think that there is anie inconsistencie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Salus Populi,</hi> and the beeing of a King and of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58502:5"/> Lords in a Nation; if they behave themselvs not as Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, to rule all at will, and without Laws: which are in the people's right to chuse and settle for themselvs and their Kings; and it is their King's onelie Prerogative, and the dutie of their Lords, to see those Laws observed: for to mee it is clearly against the Law of God and nature, that anie King or Lords should bee <hi>Magìs soluti Legibus,</hi> then anie of the meanest Subjects; or <hi>de jure</hi> bee less reproveable then they are. This beeing then my cleer judgment, that Kings and Lords are officers in a National sociëtie appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by God through men, to see Laws kept, it never came into my minde to think that their beeing in a Nation should bee inconsistent with the safetie thereof: and if you willingly grant, that all humane Constitutions or Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of men, as the Apostle call's Kings, must give place to <hi>Salus Populi,</hi> I suppose, you and I shall verie little disa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree about the Tenure of Kings and Lords; therefore when in the close of this admonition you saie, that this is <hi>altogether in question,</hi> truly I understand not how it come's to bee a question at all between us, or wherein I have given you a ground to think so; nor do I understand well what is meant by the words which follow thereupon, viz. <hi>And was otherwise determined by the major part of the Commons (when the Hous was full and free) who are our onelie competent Judges in things of this nature.</hi> I saie, I know not well what you mean by the thing which was otherwise determined: for if I dissent not from you in this, then nothing was other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise determined; as to my sens in this matter, then what you agree to. But if you would intimate, that the Hous when it was (in your sens) <hi>full and free,</hi> did determine that there should bee a King and Hous of Lords, remaining with the Hous of Commons in this Nation, as a lawful Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in their joint relations, according to the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental constitution of the State; if this bee your meaning, I fully grant it, That once it was so determined by both Houses, and by the major part of the Commons, who were your competent Judges in things of this nature. And yet now wee see it is again otherwise determined by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58502:6"/> partie of the same Commons, who declare themselvs to bee a full and free Hous (of which assertion now they are the onelie competent Judges) and according to their determination nothing is generally asserted, and in <hi>Thesi,</hi> That <hi>Salus Populi,</hi> and a King and Lords are inconsistent; but onely in <hi>Hypothesi,</hi> and particularly, That at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, there is an inconsistencie of a King and Hous of Lords with the safetie of this People: which how true or fals it is, ought not to bee disputed, becaus it cannot bee deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by you or mee; for it depend's upon the cognizance of circumstance; whereof I conceiv none of our coat are competent judges, nor anie others that are in places of sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection; but onely those that are betrusted with the higher Powers, and are about the management of their places of Trust. And if it cannot bee denied, that those that have made the alteration of the Government, were persons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trusted with power able to do what they did, and did it in the Management of their places of trust, according to the best of their understanding, for the safetie of the People, I dare not take upon mee to bee their judges, but must leav them to him under whom they pretend to stand; and must acknowledg that the alteration is of God, whose ordinatie cours it is to do, by a minor part, and by weak means, that which a major part of the world, and the greatness of the strength thereof, is not able to do. And if I perceiv that a matter is clearly determined by those whom hee hath em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploied, and who are in power to manage publick affairs by their places; although it may bee carried contrarie to my private sens and exspectation, yet I see no warrant for mee to take upon mee to make any other determination of the matter in my thoughts, then God hath don by them who have the management of his Power; nor can I see how it is lawful for anie man who cannot bring his thoughts to close with that which hath been don by others, under whose protection hee is obliged to live, to refuse to do things in themselvs lawful, just, and undeniably tending to Common safetie, onely upon this account, becaus such things are commanded by men, whom they judg to have
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58502:6"/> don that which is amiss, and beyond the line of their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer. If they who presume to judg so, were by anie right of God or men made judges of their actions, or able to call them to an account thereof before competent judges; or in a condition to stand free, and in no need of their prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, somthing, as I conceiv, might bee said for their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice: but when men can pretend to nothing of all this, but are meer Subjects, and under a Power which undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly is Supreme over them; under a power in full possession of all places of trust about them, and in a capacitie to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage the same, for the good of those that do well, and for the punishment of those that do evil; Now, I saie, for men, when things are so, to stand out and to resist such po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, not in things of an unlawful, but of a most commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, lawful, and necessarie nature in themselvs, and to think to bee obliged to do so for conscience sake, is to mee I confess, an extreme great Paradox in the profession of Christianitie, as it is an unpartial and conscionable walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before God in conformitie to his will. And if this is not the present case wherein som Ministers do stand in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position to the present Powers, I would bee glad to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified; and you will do mee a favor to shew mee wherein I do mistake either the publick or their private case in this matter.</p>
               <p>The third matter of admonition is: That I seem not to deal charitably and compassionately with those who through tendernes of conscience, in reference to Oaths and Covenants, are afraid to engage this waie <hi>(though they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage to live quietly and obeie in lawful things)</hi> by an owning of the Autoritie; and this uncharitablenes you charge upon mee from my expressions in <hi>pag.</hi> 21. of my <hi>Considerations,</hi> where I seem to saie, That such should have no protection or other benefit of Law. If I have said so of such persons, and to the end that they should bee deprived of protection, and of the benefit of equal justice; I confess it would bee somwhat rigorous and inconsistent with the spirit of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion and charitie. I am sure it was not in my design to deprive any tender conscience of anie equitable favor which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58502:7"/> may bee shewed unto them, nay I have professedly and sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely engaged my self, to use all my interest in those that are in places of power, to procure this unto them, as you may see more at large in the Reproposals, <hi>pag.</hi> 18. and 19. In the Paragraphs, which in the margent are marked for an Answer to the seventh and eight <hi>Sect.</hi> of the Proposals: and as I there have professed, so I have hitherto uprightly endeavoured; but as for that which you alledg out of the Considerations, <hi>pag.</hi> 22. of the second and third Edition, (for in the first Edition, it is <hi>page</hi> 24.) I shall desire you to consider the matter and scope of that which I saie in that place; and if then you look upon the principle, which I had before (in <hi>page</hi> 16. of the same Editions) as a ground of Justice in this Case, perhaps you will see caus to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse mee from the uncharitableness, which you charge upon mee, as towards tender Consciences; for there I speak concerning an objection against the subscribing of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, taken from the apprehension of offending godlie people by subscribing of it; my scope is to answer that Objection upon this presupposal, that, hee who take's it, is not, as to his own Conscience, scrupled at the taking of the Engagement; but is to bee swaied meerly by his consideration of others: here then to such a one I saie, that <hi>caeteris paribus</hi> (for this is expresly supposed in the propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal of the Case) there is more caus to apprehend a danger of offence in not subscribing, then in subscribing; becaus there are more offences (even three to one) in the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, in case of not subscribing: for here I have caus as well as there to apprehend the offence, not onely of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie godlie brethren, but also of Superiors, and of my self in point of safetie; and these two last offences I join in this, that the Magistrate to whom I refuse to give an as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surance of my fidelitie, may take that refusal, as a just caus given him to denie mee necessarie protection and safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. For I suppose that the Rule is without all exception, that <hi>Protectio trahit Allegianciam; &amp; vice versâ Allegiancia Protectionem &amp; è contra:</hi> now whether this bee the same case which you charge upon mee, I shall leav it to your second
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58502:7"/> thoughts to consider; for here I presuppose my self not at all scrupled in my Conscience, but to bee swaied by meer outward considerations of dangers: and that amongst other dangers I might justly apprehend this; that if I will not shew my self faithful to the Magistrate, who is over mee, I may fear to bee deprived of the benefit which otherwise I might reap from his office which is necessarie protection.</p>
               <p>As for the seeming Contradiction mentioned in your fourth exception, you will easily of your self reconcile it, and perceiv your mistake, if you construe my words right, and leav not out the additional claus, put in of purpose to limit the approbation, the ratifying Consent and the obligation towards the present establishment, which I mean to declare by my subscription; the claus which you have left out in your quotation of my words (which make's them seem to you contradictorie to themselvs) is this; <hi>But thus far onely as I have said.</hi> Construe then the whole period by a little transposition of their words in their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, thus, <hi>I mean to declare, by my Subscription, my approbation of my ratifying consent unto, and my obligation towards the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent establishment; but onely thus far as have said. viz.</hi> in the three paragraphs immediately going before, wherein I li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit in the first, the approbation, in the second, the ratifying consent, and in the third, the obligation towards the establishment: to shew, that although I think not my self bound up by my subscription of the engagement, to the particulars mentioned in the Proposals, which are said to bee different from the Duties, which Subjects owe to Superiors; yet I am willing to acknowledg som kinde of approbation of ratifying consent, and of obligation to the establishment included in the subscription; <hi>viz.</hi> such as is agreeable to those duties, and such as I formerly had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed, although then I will not grant, that the subscrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the words of the engagement doth imploie those Consequences, whereunto the Proposers would strain them, which they saie are opposite to their Oaths and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants: yet I refuse not to admit of som other Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58502:8"/> which I limit, and declare to bee consistent with the Oaths and Covenants; the particulars inferred upon the Subscription by the Proposers, I saie, are things which go beyond a clear and known dutie; and I conceiv, that the words of the Engagement give no ground to interpret the Act of Subscription so; but that I may notwithstanding this rejection of those particulars, infer other particulars of the same kinde, agreeable unto a Dutie upon the same Act of Subscription, is nothing of Contradiction, as to my understanding, nor I hope will bee to yours when you shall consider better of it; and shall not leav out the adversative particle, and the claus which refer you to the limitation, which I think should bee heeded about those inferences.</p>
               <p>The fifth thing which you offer, is the hard censure of want of sinceritie, you think is pronounced against all those, that can <hi>acquiesce</hi> in nothing; but in such a Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as shall bee made either by themselvs, or their Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors to their content; but if you look well to my words, you will finde also here a cleer mistake of my meaning; for my aim is not to speak of all those that have anie doubts or scruples about this busines; as if none of them were sincere, that will or cannot <hi>acquiesce</hi> in anie thing els but in such a Declaration; I saie, my words speak not indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely of all such; but they express onely these proposers. For I saie distinctly, that in the proposers aim will appear no sinceritie in reference to these Proposals, if there is nothing, but this that will content them; becaus in their Proposals they seem by offering at a Treatie, and by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siring to have matters of doubt debated, and reconciled, to seek a rational waie of satisfaction to themselvs. Now saie I, when this waie shall bee offered to them, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered upon, if they then will not follow it ingenuously; but will stand peremptorily upon their own preconceived terms, and agree to nothing, but what they themselvs have fancied, must bee declared; In this case I saie it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that the aim of the Proposers in the matter of their proposals, is not sincere towards the procurement of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58502:8"/> and a just waie of satisfaction, which they seem to desire; if you observ then that you mistake the Case by your not heeding the particular Subject whereof I speak, and the presupposals which I laie as the ground of that Censure; I suppose you will absolv mee from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitableness in this matter; for truly I believ manie to bee sincerely scrupled; and yet so weak that without making or receiving a Declaration in their own terms, they cannot bee satisfied; nay, I have met with som such. God forbid, then I should condemn them all for this, to have no sinceritie in their scruples; but if men make proposals of waies to have their Scruples taken away, and then will not at all observ the same; but without all rational and ingenuous proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will peremptorily prescribe their own terms to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; I think it no uncharitableness to saie, that such men in making such proposals have no sinceritie, and that this is my meaning in that passage; if you look over it again, I make no doubt you will finde it to bee so.</p>
               <p>The sixt Admonition doth compare that which I saie of the Proposers, in reference to the continuance of their Proposals, <hi>page</hi> 29. with what they might saie of mee in reference to my late papers; as for the expressions which I have used in that place, I shall not stand to justifie them; I shall rather confess that they should have been spared, or otherwise delivered; for when I look upon them, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them with the design which I had in that last Section, I finde that I am carried further thereby then I did purpose to proceed; for my purpose in the later part of that Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, was not directly to charge the proposers with anie politick design, but onely to let them see, as by waie of Admonition, how far both the matter and the contrivance of the proposals might bee liable to such an interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; if anie would give waie to suspiciousness, which I do iteratively profess my self to bee free from, and through charitie unwilling to entertein: yet upon the supposal, that it is possible som such thing might bee in the minde of som of the Proposers, I would shew the waie how even in that Case they might receiv satisfaction; but the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58502:9"/> which you have noted; are I perceiv more then this design come's to; for they rise up to a positive, and direct charge of that where of I intended onely to give by waie of supposition, a warning, as of that which possibly might bee. Thus I observ by my self, that when our spirits dwell upon objects of evil surmises, although it maie bee for a good and harmless aim, yet they may easily bee heated above their just measure, and lose their waie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the end of edification, which cannot bee followed otherwise then in the Spirit of Love. As for my papers, if anie will examine them, so as to finde out the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, by which it maie bee probably suspected, that my aim is rather to pleas a prevailing partie, then to advance Peace and Truth in righteousnes towards all, without par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialitie, I shall not take it ill at his hands; but rather thank him, and blessing God for his brotherlie care, trie my heart, and judg my thoughts by the occasion thereof, which is all that I would have the proposers do, about the matter whereof I intended to give them warning.</p>
               <p>As for the last matter, which you mention out of <hi>page</hi> 21. of the Reproposals, that even good men are too sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to admit of self-mixtures in their best actions; and that I am not to bee exempted from this weakness, no more then others; I shall freely confess it, to bee a truth, and declare moreover, that when I wrote that period of the discours, I was not without that verie consideration of my self; and therefore I did set it down the rather to bee a Caution for my self; least I might neglect the obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of mine own spirit, and cours in these matters wherewith I have begun to meddle, which I declare to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle withal for this onelie purpose; that I maie hold forth the waie, how to seek impartially peace by a rule, and to follow holiness with all men, without which no man shall see the Lord. I thank you then for putting mee in minde of this my condition, and hope that God will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able mee to observ also the rest of that, which you sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest in the close of this admonition.</p>
               <p>To that which you add in shutting up these matters
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58502:9"/> which you have represented; I shall not replie much, onely should bee sorrie, that those fears, you speak of, should have anie <hi>fundamentum in re,</hi> more then in the tenderness of your fear: I can truly saie, that my labors, according to the best of my skill, do tend to prevent that, which maie heighten the heat of the Magistrate's indignation against the truly godlie, by setting before them the Rules of an unblameable walking, and by discovering the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of a deviation from the same; therefore to let them see the faults, in which som manifestly are taken, and which may bring guilt upon all, that they may avoid, prevent, and rectifie the same, is no unfriendlie office; nor can the discoverie of failings, which sheweth the Caus with the Cure, make anie breaches wider, but I conceiv that a thorow-searching is the onelie sound waie of healing, and closing of our wounds. I can saie with a good conscience, that I have all along endeavored, upon all occasions, to cast water upon the heats of both sides, lest they might break out into a flame; and that I have sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licited, and will sollicite a moderation towards tender Consciences with the best of my industrie: but the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of som tumultuously-clamorous spirits spoil's all.</p>
               <p>The Paragraph which begin's with a consideration of the generaltie of the Church of <hi>Scotland;</hi> and end's with a second complaint of my censuring all with unsinceritie, that take not the Engagement, is either assented unto for the main, or hath been rectified in that, wherein the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stake lies by that which hath been said heretofore; onely this I would have observed, that although I will not slight the judgment of anie Church, but think reverently of all, yet, that the general opinion of no Church, far less of a forreign Church ought so to bee regarded, as to swaie anie man's judgment concerning the Civil Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of anie State in outward matters: for in such Cases everie mans Reason, and the Relations under which hee live's, must guid his Conscience to the knowledg of his Dutie; and what ever is don upon anie other considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or implicit concurrance with the generalitie of others,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58502:10"/> doth ordinarily becom a snare to the Conscience.</p>
               <p>Lastly, the Arguments which you use, to perswade mee not to laie anie more load on those, who are already sinking under the burden of doubts and perplexities, I do consider as true motives to that dutie which you press upon mee, whereunto, by God's grace I purpose not to bee wanting henceforth, although I am not yet made to see, that heretofore I have been guiltie of that Charge, which this exhortation doth presuppose mee liable unto: but I can easily, without trouble of minde, God bee thanked, bear with more then such surmises, and Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures amount unto; if I can but gain thereby an unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiciate hearing of that, which hereafter I may saie towards the easing of those that are burdened with the troubles outwardly, and doubts inwardly, which they occasion to themselvs, by walking either without, or contrarie to a Rule; for give mee leav to saie the truth, that in the disquirie of these things which are agitated I pretend; truly I intend, and really endeavor to think nothing; far less to saie, or act anie thing without a clear rule; and if anie time I can give you no account of that, which I saie or do, by a Rule which hath led my thoughts to bring forth those speeches and actions, I hope I shall bee assisted with grace, patiently to bear the blame which I shall deserv for so doing; I give you therefore free leav to call mee to an account; for I know I must answer one daie at a greater tribunal then yours, and I count it a small matter to bee judged by men; it doth not trouble mee at all; yet I shall never despise the judgment of anie that may reflect upon mee; for I conceiv, that God doth speak unto mee by everie one who is conscionable, and take's notice of mee, that I maie bee the more sollicitous to approve my waie unto him; As I therefore am very willing to bear the word of the exhortation in the dutie, and motives which you laie before mee; so I shall intreat you to do the like, in that which I shall briefly represent unto you. First, let mee intreat those who desire the hand of autoritie not to bee heavier upon them, then as yet it hath been (for as yet I
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58502:10"/> know of nothing don to anie) not to provoke Autori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but to diswade those, that set themselvs to incens the people against their rulers in their pulpits; one turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent spirit in this waie will procure more wrath to all, then ten intercessors can allaie; for such men make chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table intercessors ashamed to open their mouth towards the Magistrate, seeing they are manifestly seditious. Can a Magistrate bee perswaded to suffer himself to bee tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled upon? Moderate the fierce non-subscribers in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and Countrie from beeing injurious, and I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent God will caus them to finde a reciprocation of love from Autoriti<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Secondly, let those who are not turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and finde themselvs burdened, and pinched with straits, bee entreated to condiscend to the use of conscio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, and rational means of easing themselvs, which by aimable Treaties and Conferences rightly ordered may bee brought to pass; and what aversness hath been hitherto in som, against this waie of finding eas (though they have been begged to it) I am loath to relate: but if it had been duly enterteined, I am sure mistakes might have been rectified, which have heightned men's spirits, and brought us to extremities.</p>
               <p>You maie perceiv, that my heart is enlarged towards you for your candor; the Lord grant us the conduct of his spirit, to make use of each other's good inclinations to allaie heats and jealousies; whereunto, although I have offered my self with all the candor and humilitie that I could imagine, to bee required of God, or acceptable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to men; yet I have not been able to obtein anie reciproca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from anie of the Brethren here in <hi>London,</hi> who differ in judgment about the present Engagement; not so much as one meeting, to bee able to speak together, though with much earnestness desired by mee, and whether the iniquitie (as I conceiv) of this and som other unchristi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an usages from the brethren, hath not a litle distempered mee, when I wrote the last piece, whereat you are now of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, I cannot well tell; but when I call my self to an account of ym thoughts, it seem's som such leaven did lie
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58502:11"/> then at the bottom, and was stirred to a paroxism of fermentation which brought up som froth: but God is able to turn all to the best, if wee despise not one anothe'rs admonitions, but receiv them as in his presence, and give them as in the name of Christ in his love: if there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you will let mee hear from you again, and let the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Brethren, whom I am sorrie to have offended, for want of due consideration of all tempers, know, what I have said for their and your satisfaction, you will oblige mee in the bowels of Christ, more and more to approve my self,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <lb/>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your faithful and affectionate<lb/> Servant for the Gospel of<lb/> Peace and Truth</hi>
                     <lb/> JOHN DURIE.</signed>
                  <lb/>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Westminster</hi>
                     <lb/>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Febr.</hi> 21.<lb/>
                        <hi>Anno</hi> 1649/50.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="letter">
               <head>The second Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Reverend Sir!</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Return you manie thanks, for your pains and patience, in seeking to give satisfaction to the doubts propounded, in the paper I directed to you, I acquainted som of my godlie friends with it, who, though they bee yet unsatisfied touching the main question; yet most of them are fully satisfied touching your own candor and integritie, and do now think, that which you did by your writings, was don upon conscientious grounds, or not to serv the times. I will not bee so uncivil or unthankful, as to trouble you now with anie tedious replie, (though much might bee said) but onely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you with som scruples, as still do pinch som pious minds, who would bee glad, if they could meet with anie help for the right clearing of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>First,</hi> they do not fully apprehend what you mean, by that <hi>known dutie</hi> which you often urge; if it bee, that wee engage to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58502:11"/>
                  <hi>live quietly &amp; make no disturbance</hi> this hath been often offered, but will not satisfie. If it bee <hi>to submit to the higher powers,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caus they are of God: you know a thing may bee said to bee <hi>of God</hi> two waies, namely, either in regard of his <hi>providence,</hi> or of his <hi>precept.</hi> Now the difficult is, whether <hi>providence</hi> alone may bee the rule of own actions, or approbation of other men's: if it may, then wee may approve of <hi>Absolon's</hi> incest, becaus God saith hee did it, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. 12. And so all evil actions of evil men are guid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his providence: If <hi>precept</hi> bee needful, they cannot see how the present higher powers are of God: becaus they were not called of God; but have chosen and set up themselvs in these places; for however som of them were at first chosen for other purposes (as to contribute their help in making Laws, and seeing the Laws well executed) yet they were never chosen to bee the supreme power of the Nation So that this new Government beeing neither grounded upon the old Law of the Nation, nor anie new agreement of their representations (the greatest part of them beeing either by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence withheld, or deterred from coming) this make's it difficult to discern how the higher powers may bee said to bee of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> they think that Oaths to God do oblige not onely for the present, but for the future, according to the sens wherein they were both imposed and taken: but it was neither the intention of the imposers, nor their's when they took them, that kinglie Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment should bee taken away, or that the present King and his posteritie should bee deprived of it, but the quite contrarie; for they did swear that they would bee drawn by no power on earth from their allegiance to them. Neither will the King's miscarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age bee a sufficient ground to absolv them, from their Oath of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance to him and his; becaus the Oath was absolute, not conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal. Besides, look how God command's obedience. So they did swear obedience; but all the commands of obedience to higher powers, both in <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. and in other places, are absolute, and not upon condition of their good carriage. In like manner, as hee command's servants to bee subject to their masters: not onely to those who were good and gentle, but to those who were froward, and who did them wrong, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 18. Neither would there bee anie place left for suffering, either by Subjects or servants, if obedience were onely conditional.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:58502:12"/>
               <p> Thirdly, They think that though they bee not competent judges of State matters, yet they are competent judges of their own acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (for which they must give an account to God, and they know, whatever they shall do doubtfully, they do sinfully <hi>(for whatever is not of faith is sin)</hi> and the owning of the present power as of God is doubtful to them, (at least) upon the grounds before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned. Besides, by subscribing, they do not onely own the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent power, but also the imposing of the Engagement (if not direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet indirectly) which they cannot see how it agree's with the rule that require's higher powers, should bee a terror to the evil, not to the good, as by this means they are.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, for matter of offence, they think those whom the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle bid's us take heed not to offend, are the weak brethren, now hee is a weak brother who think's a thing to bee a thing unlawful (suppose it bee lawful) becaus it seem's to bee against som rule of the word (as this Engagement seem's to bee against the rule, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing oaths and promises, that they should bee kept though to our own hindrance. And thus the refusers onely, not the imposers, or those who have already taken it, are to bee accounted weak Brethren.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, for the judgment of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or other Divines, they think, that in clear evident truths, anie humane judgment dissenting, is not much to bee regarded, but that in dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult, doubtful things the spirits of the Prophets ought to bee sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the Prophets, els wee shall overthrow all use of Synods, and follow the tract of Enthusiasts, and such as think themselvs guided by an infallible spirit. Thus I have been bold to open the doubts of som good men unto you, hoping you will entertein them with som secrecie, and the like spirit of love and meekness as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and at your convenient leisure you will not refuse to yield them a little further help. Our good God guid us so in all our thoughts and actions, that wee may neither do, nor think anie thing that may bee displeasing to him.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours in the best bond.</signed>
                  <lb/>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>March this</hi> 25.<lb/> 1650.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="answer">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:58502:12"/>
               <head>The Answer to the second Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Reverend Sir!</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YEsterday's late coming home, I found yours of the 25<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of <hi>March;</hi> whereby I perceived that mine was com'n safe to your hands; and that you make a charitable construction of the things which I did write unto you; which is no smal refreshment unto my spirit, in the midst of these heats wherein wee are fallen, which God hath sent for our trial; and which will bee a great advantage to the purifying of our souls, if wee bebave our selvs order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly therein. As for the scruples which you are pleased to acquaint mee withall, that som help may bee supplyed for the cleering thereof; although they do not stumble mee, but mee think's I see light enough through them; yet I cannot saie that they are not to bee counted scruples; or that they are easily to bee cleared; for although to mee they are no great difficulties; yet I conceiv to others they may bee, who reflect not upon matters by such principles as I do; and with those considerations which I take up: nor is it in the power of anie man, to make another ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of his Principles and Considerations; but God alone is able to do it; and all that wee can bee helpful to one another in, is to offer to one another so much light as wee have received; and if wee offer it in love, without partialitie, and with a true meaning to advance Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness and Holiness, it may, by God's blessing, becom useful unto Edification; chiefly, if wee strive for one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other towards God with our praiers, that wee may becom helpers of each other's joie, through the grace which hee bestoweth upon us, to profit withall. I shall therefore, not undertake to resolv these scruples; for that would bee presumption, God alone can do it; but I shall humbly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to those pious mindes, that are scrupled, my light; with all truth and sinceritie, as it is in my heart; praying to God, that if it bee from his spirit, it may so appear to them, as to clear their understandings from mistakes.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:58502:13"/>
               <p> The first scruple you mention, is concerning my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression, what I mean by <hi>that known dutie<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, which I often urge.</hi> I wish you had pointed out a place or two, that I might have been able to speak more directly to your sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, then now I can do; perhaps, I shall saie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that, till I bee told, where that expression is used (for I cannot readily light upon it, having cursorily look't upon the considerations) I think that I have meant throughout, nothing els, but a <hi>seeking of the Peace and welfare of the societie wherein wee live;</hi> for I think it is a known dutie in Christianitie, that wee should serv one another through love for our good; and not bee taken off from this cours, so far as others are capable to receiv good from us, notwithstanding the evil which may bee in them, the dutie which the Apostle mention's, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 14; 15, 16. is that, which I would have all men, but chiefly Ministers in these times to laie to heart: and you have the third, or fourth Edition of the Considerations, you will see at the end of it, the extract of a Letter; and my Answer thereunto, which conteineth that dutie, which I conceiv to bee clear, and known to all, who will look upon the Engagement in the obvious sens thereof.</p>
               <p>By this you see, that I mean not onely a passive, but an active dutifulness, in things good and lawful under the present powers, let them bee what they will; as for that which you scruple, to submit to the powers, <hi>becaus they are of God,</hi> as if that reason were not sufficient, becaus, things may bee said to bee of God, either Prudentially, or Preceptively; now <hi>Providence alone</hi> (saie you) <hi>is not the rule of our own actions, or approbation of other men's.</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess this to bee so. But yet I finde, that the Apostle's rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, why hee command's all Christians to bee subject to higher powers, to bee none other but this; viz. <hi>Becaus there is no power but of God; and becaus the powers that bee, are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of God;</hi> Rom. 13. 1. So that the exception which you make seem's to mee, to bee directly against the Apostle's rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soning, which I suppose you intended not to contradict: and if the Romane Christians under <hi>Nero</hi> would have
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58502:13"/> disobeied lawful and Moral Commands, wherein the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle onely bid's them submit, they might have made your exception against his beeing of God, as fully as this is made against the present powers over us. If then the scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple strike's rather at the force of the Apostle's Argument, then at anie thing els, I think, I am bound to vindicate his reasoning from the force of the doubt; which may bee don thus; that God's appointment of a power over us, is a just caus to oblige us to submission thereunto, whether hee doth it Providentially or Preceptively; or both waies: I saie that in things lawful and good, Submission is due, becaus the power in place is of God; and hee that resist's it, resist's God's ordinance, saith the Apostle. But you will saie, if it bee onely providentially of God, so was <hi>Abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom's</hi> incest, and is no rule, either to warrant mine own, or for mee to approve other's mens actions? to this I saie; it is true, when you have a precept to walk by, you must not make God's acts of Providence over you a rule, to warrant anie designs which contradict the precepts, which are given you to walk by; but when things are to bee look't upon by you; not as your own, or other men's Actions; but as determined events, which God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to fall out, in a way of Justice and Judgment; then you ought not to set your self against the same, but in things lawful ought to approve the same; so of <hi>Abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom's</hi> incest, wee must saie that God's providence or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered it for judgment over <hi>David,</hi> for a punishment of his Adulterie; and in that respect it was good; but as it was the effect of <hi>Achitophel's</hi> wicked Policie to make matters de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperate, and a satisfying of <hi>Absolom's</hi> lust, and a disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor to his Father, and a shameless act, it was evil, and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to bee condemned; thus in the events of things befal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len to us, which are the changes of powers over us; first the King, then the Parlament, then the Armie; and now again the Parliament; these events in themselvs are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good nor evil to us, as God hath brought them about, and ordered their succession for judgment, they were all good; and everie power in it's own time was to bee sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58502:14"/> unto, by those that were under it, becaus it was of God for the time over them, and if in things lawful they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted it: they did resist the ordinance of God, &amp; might justly bee brought under condemnation by it; but each of these powers, as they might bee in the persons of unjust men, who by subtiltie or violence (as <hi>Absolom</hi> and <hi>Achitophel</hi> did) thrust out others of the possession of their places to attein their ends; in this respect they were evil; and as men contrarie in their walking to the will of God, they must not bee approved of: that is to saie, their ambition, fraud, violent practices, &amp;c. are not to bee approved of: Nevertheless, if God's Providence order it so, that they bee set up as the higher power; I suppose they are to bee look't upon as ordained by God, to that place, and obeied in things good and lawful: their unlawful coming to their places, after that they have gotten full possession, doth not absolv anie private soul from the obligation of beeing subject, and obedient in things good and lawful. Thus Providence, as to events become's a Rule to oblige us, to do things for our selvs good and lawful; and to approve of the same in others.</p>
               <p>You saie, <hi>if precept bee needful, they cannot see how the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent powers are of God: becaus they were not called of God: but have chosen and set up themselvs.</hi> To this I saie, that certainly precept is needful for everie man to walk by in all his actions, and what hee doth without the warrant of a Rule, is don sinfully: but yet I must add this, that it doth not follow, that if the powers which are in place, are not so com to their place, that I can see that they are called by God to it, according to a precept, that therefore I must, or may think they are not of God; for although their Calling, or coming to their place is not to mee clear, to bee conformable to a precept; yet it may bee so to themselvs, and to others; and I am not to bee a Judg in things of that nature; but I suppose that it is cleerly contrarie to all Rule and Precept, that which they have don to com to their places; and that not I onely, but all men, and they themselvs will confess it; and saie as <hi>Cesar</hi> did; <hi>Si violan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58502:14"/> est jus, regnandi caussâ violandum est; in caeteris pietatem colito.</hi> Suppose (I saie) this to bee so; shall I therefore saie, that they are not the present power, when I see them actually in full possession of the place of all power over mee? or shall I saie that they are not of God; when I hear the Apostle saying clearly, without anie limitation in the negative, first, <hi>there is no power; but of God;</hi> and then in the affirmative; <hi>the powers that bee, are ordained of God:</hi> all powers then are of God one waie or other; and beeing of him, I must not resist, but submit in things lawful. Look upon M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Perkins</hi> in his Treatise of Callings, where hee speak's of Christ, and the Apostles submitting themselvs to the powers, that then were in and over <hi>Judea;</hi> and <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vini. Justit. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 20. <hi>parag.</hi> 28. speaking of <hi>Nebuchadne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar,</hi> whom hee set's up as a precedent of an usurped power to bee obeied; hee hath these words, <hi>observandum est quâ ratione ipsum Dominus stabiliat. Detuli, inquit, Nebuchadnezari Regnum; quare servite illi &amp; vivite; cuicunque ergò delatum fuisse regnum constabit, ei serviendum esse nè dubitemus, atque simulae in Regium fastigium quempiam evehit Dominus; testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam nobis facit suam voluntatem, quòd regnare illum velit,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Touching the calling of these men to their places; and what the nature of their place is; how far they are autorized ordinarily, or extraordinarily to make Laws, or see them executed; and whether by their chois they bee made the supreme power or no, is not a thing of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie private man's cognizance, so as to bee bound to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminate it; and according to his private opinion, to bee obliged to act, or not to act for Conscience sake with them, or against them: I saie, to mee such considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are heterogeneal to my calling, and whatever I think of them, and of their calling to their places, that is not material, as to the point of dutie, which I owe them, as beeing in full possession of the government. As for themselvs, they think their calling doth bear them out in everie thing which they have don; and I finde not that my calling doth bear mee out to argue, as som do, the matter against them: but if it may bee a satisfaction to you, or
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58502:15"/> to others, I shall bee willing to let you know more at large, what they saie for themselvs in these particulars, which truly I know not how anie bodie can well answer; but whether their allegations can bee answered or not, it is not further heeded by mee, then may serv to give o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers som in sight into that, which they seem rationally to alledg for themselvs.</p>
               <p>Thus I have told you my sens of your first scruple; the second is concerning Oaths. The promissorie Oaths which men make one to another, are obliging, or not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging, according to the possibilitie and lawfulness of the intentions of those, that impose and take them; and I conceiv, the taker of an Oath is no further obliged to the intention of the imposer, then either is cleerly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed by him in the words of the oath; or in som previ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, or subsequent Declaration, assented unto by the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker; or then the taker doth declare himself to bee obliged thereunto: therefore to prevent mistakes, I did for mine own part, both in the national Covenant, and in this En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement declare my sens and intention in taking them; which beeing allowed, I finde my self obliged thereto, now if it fall out, that the imposer's intention doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (as upon good and valid grounds men's intentions may bee altered) from what it was at first (for if the thing intended, which was once lawful and possible, by change of circumstances becom's vnlawful, and impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and this bee made known by the imposer of the oath to him that take's it,) then the Question must bee, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in such case the taker is not absolved from his obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? there bee manie things in the National Covenant of different natures; som are by circumstances changeable, som altogether unchangeable, the Relation which the two Nations have each to other; if either of the Nations break it (as it is in the power of all Rulers, to break, or keep entire friendlie relations with their neighbor Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) how far the other is bound to keep it, I think it not dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to bee determined, friends are relatives; and I can bee no longer in a relation of friendship to anie, then hee will
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:58502:15"/> own friendship with mee; if he break his Covenant there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and make himself an enemie to mee, I am not bound anie longer by the tie of that Covenant to bee his friend: yet other ties of an higher nature may bee upon mee, to keep mee from beeing his enemie: for there is a mid'st be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween friendship, and hostilitie; and if the Rulers of the State, wherein I live, bring mee under a National relation with a neighbor Nation, to bee in friendship with it at one time; and at another time bring mee to contrarie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation towards it; I conceiv that I am concluded by what they do either waie; and that in such a case the breach of Covenant doth lie at their door, and not at mine, if I in my place have been careful not to give occasion thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and thus I conceiv all other actions of a publick na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that I am concluded therein; to stand under the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, which those that manage the same bring upon one thereby, as to outward matters: though not as to a professed concurrence of my intentions with them, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then they expresly call mee thereunto, and I expresly declare my concurrence in that waie, and when I have declared my intentions, then so far as I declare them, and as they remain possible and lawful by mee, to bee prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted in my waie; I am bound to intend them; and I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv, that they are not to be counted longer possible, nor lawful for mee to bee prosecuted in my waie; then they are consistent with the main and fundamental Duties of my calling and place, as I am a Christian, and as I am a Subject and a profitable member to the Common-wealth wherein I live; for all particular obligations, whether confirmed by oaths, or otherwise, are perpetually subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate in their nature, and presupposed by a <hi>tacit</hi> conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to bee consistent with these, or otherwise to bee <hi>ipso facto</hi> void. By these general Rules, and maximes concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing promissorie oaths between man and man, in matters of publick concernment; wherein, I by my place am to bee concluded by others that are over mee; I think my self free from perjurie, if a change fall out therein, so as to make mee incapable to prosecute the intentions once
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58502:16"/> sincerely taken up; for the intention of the taker of an oath beeing constant, and sincere to that which hee hath promised, according to the circumstances of matters which then were in beeing, when the promise was made, doth ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solv him before God, and his own conscience, from per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurie; for hee will profess himself alwaies bound to prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the same intention, and will endeavor it to the utmost of his abilitie, so long as those circumstances last, which make the intention lawful and possible; but if the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances which made his intention lawful at first, bee afterward altered so, that the intention doth becom un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, if prosecuted under those circumstances; then it is no breach of promise in him, if hee doth not prosecute his first intention; for it is not lawful so to intend the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secution of anie outward humane business; as to oblige our selvs, in what cases and circumstances soëver to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; Conscience can bee obliged to follow nothing so ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely, but the will of God; and although no conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on bee expressed in promissorie oaths when they are taken, yet in the verie nature of them, the conditions which I have mentioned are implied, and need never to bee menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned: if you will now applie these positions to your se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond scruple, and reflect upon the intentions, which then were taken up towards the King's Person and Autoritie, as circumstances then were; and the obligation in private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, such as wee are, to prosecute them as circumstances now are, you will perhaps finde light to eas you of your scruple in this matter. For I shall for mine own part declare this; that, if things were now as formerly they were, when the Covenant was offered, I would finde my self obliged to prosecute the effect thereof, in reference to the King now, as then I was bound to do; but things beeing so altered, that there is no King in beeing; but another Government over mee, I am absolved from the former relation, by those that manage publick affairs, and obliged to intend the duties of a true Christian, and good Subject, under the present relations wherein God hath set mee. As for those that have taken away that object of my former Allegiance,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58502:16"/> which went under the name of a King, and brought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mee the necessitie of this change of intention, by their acting in publick affairs; I am none of their judges, but must leav them to him, to whom they are accountable of their Administrations; if they in making the change did according to that, which they thought in conscience to bee their dutie, they will fare the better for it in the end: but if they had another aim, then to discharge their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science in their dutie, it will bee wors with them; and this is all that I am bound to saie for them, as to this in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral.</p>
               <p>Now the particulars of your Scruple on this Subject run's out upon the facts of other men (which are not your Guilt) to shew the guilt which they seem to have incurred by altering the government from Monarchie to Democra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: for you saie that they swore never to bee drawn by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie power on earth from their Allegiance to the King and his Posteritie; and that their intention was not to deprive, but to preserv the King and his Posteritie in their govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. I confess it was so; and yet you see that the rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion once intended to bee mainteined towards him and his Posteritie is altered; and if you ask them the Caus, they will tell you, that they have altered their intention justly and necessarily upon warrantable grounds; as that the nature of their promise of Allegiance to him and his posteritie was not absolute, but Conditionate; that in the third Article of the National Covenant, the Conditions implicitely understood in the Oath of Allegiance are expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citely mentioned: that his (viz. the King's) Cross wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to these Conditions (although they intended to maintein their Allegiance) hath forced them from it, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their will, that it is no power, nor fear that hath made them to alter their purpose; but a necessarie dutie for publick safetie to discharge their trust; this they will saie; and they will denie that which you saie, that the Oath was meant absolutely and without all respect to Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; as if Allegiance should have been due unto him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out anie respect to his Legal standing and Capacitie; and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58502:17"/> if Allegiance was onlie due to him in this respect; then it was first due to the Law it self; and to the Law-making power before it was due to him; and to him onlie as sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate thereunto: If therefore his Miscarriage be such as to intend the overthrow of that; by which he only could stand; then he overthrow's himself, and no bodie can help him to stand without a foundation or is obliged to it. This they will plead to justifie their proceeding to an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration. And then to that which you saie further; viz. that Obedience is commanded in an absolute sens, and not upon Condition of their good carriage: that it is comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as that which Servants ow to froward Masters; <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. &amp; 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 18. (I say) to this they will confess, that such a subjection is indeed Commanded to everie private person, and due to the powers that are in plenarie posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of the government; from their Subjects; but they will denie that the Parliament or those that are emploied by their autoritie are to bee look't upon as private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, or as Subjects in their actings: they will tell you: that all the power of the King is virtually in the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and eminently above him in a higher sphere of tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stees and representatives of the Nation; Whose sitting to act in a capacitie above him doth not onlie subordinate him in his waie of acting for the time of their Sitting: but doth in som sort suspend his whole influence upon the Subject as to government: which King <hi>Iames</hi> well understood, and therefore called the Parlament a Societie of 400 Kings, and himself for the time as no bodie: for hee is but as a Servant to see the laws which are made executed; but that the trustees and representatives of the Nation have the law-making power in them by the law of nature and the posi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Law of the Land. And lastly when you saie that there will be no place left for suffering; if obedience bee only conditional, they will tell you that Parliaments are not called by God and nature, nor in the intention of the Nation to suffer, but to rectifie the Causes of unjust suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings; and to reduce the exorbitance of Kings into a right order. Now when they, who are in places of power, saie
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58502:17"/> say all this, who is it amongst the private Subjects that can justly contest with them? or controle them? except hee have an immediate Commission to them from the most High; and if none without such a Commission is obliged to judg them, their failings are no matter of scruple to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie privat man's Conscience, they may bee a matter of grief and praier for them, for why must I bee scrupled at doing that which is my dutie at present, becaus I suspect another hath not don his dutie, of whom yet I am not set to bee a Judg.</p>
               <p>The third scruple is this; that all Subjects are to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed a Competencie of judgment concerning their own actions, though not of State-matters: becaus unto God they are accountable for whatsoëver they shall do: and if they do anie thing doubtfully, they sin. Now the owning of the present power as of God, is doubtfull to them; if therefore having the forementioned grounds of scruple they do own it, they will sin; it is therefore necessarie for them either to have the grounds of their scruple cleered or not to own them, if the doubt cannot bee cleered.</p>
               <p>To all this I shall saie; that it is a truth that men must bee allowed to bee Judges of their own actions, and that if they do anie thing without Faith, it is sin in them, if therefore they are in doubt of that which is offered to bee don, I think they are bound to suspend the doing thereof, till they bee cleer, that they can do it without sin. But then also I conceiv they are bound to use means to have their Scruple cleered one waie or other; and that in the use of those means they ought not to intangle their Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence into a judicature of matters which are beyond the sphere of their own actings; but should only strictly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire what their own dutie is in their special Callings; and if the Brethren would have don this; or could have been perswaded to have entred upon anie rational cours tending to accomplish this. I am confident much of the danger, if not all, whereinto they have cast themselves and the publick, might have been prevented, and they cleered in the scruples which they entertain and put into
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58502:18"/> the heads of other men. I speak this concerning som, whose actings I know have had a great influence upon others; whose scruples have run out upon the interpretation of State-matters, whereof they were not at all made Judges, either in publick to censure those that do manage the same; or otherwise to possess their fellow-Subjects by fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister informations with jealousies against them; if these had not made themselvs <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in this matter, but would have conteined their thoughts within their own limits, and the bounds of the Rule; they would have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented the snare's, whereinto by such considerations they have brought their own Consciences, and the Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of others that respect them; for mine own part, I did endeavor (foreseeing that the custom alreadie taken up to meddle in these matters, would upon this occasion bee more then ever followed) to prevent the further pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; or to take off by conscionable rules som that were too much inclined that waie, by a Treatise upon that Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, first in brief, and then more at large; but this was look't upon as a time-serving practice: and a cloak to sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful compliances for private ends: and afterward, when the Hous of <hi>Parliament</hi> begun to consider of an engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as a ground to settle matters and the mindes of men, to entertein a mutual relation of friendship one with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, in a Common-wealth-waie; before the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was published while's men were full of fears, and apprehensions about it, what it might tend unto; I did negotiate with som of our chief leading men, for a private conference, to bring on, with their concurrence, a Treatie, between godlie and dissenting Brethren, lest upon new emergencies (as is fallen out) wee might bee irrecove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably distracted, and divided within our own thoughts, and towards one another; or rather from each other by jealousies to incline them hereunto, I did represent, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing would bee our preservation, but our right under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing of one another in that wherein wee do agree, to hold forth our union therein to all the world; and our determination of som regular cours to prevent offences,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58502:18"/> and breaches for the things wherein there might bee som disagreement, and diversitie of opinions, which upon new emergencies might arise, or bee cast in perhaps to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide us; here then I proposed this Method, seeing it was apparent enough, that Satan's aim in all these confusions, was, to overthrow the profession of Christianitie, and put down the Ministerie thereof by gaining, and taking an opportunitie in this change of Government, and time of licentiousness, to vent all manner of damnable Heresies against the fundamental Truths, which are after godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in Christ Jesus; First by dividing the mindes of the witnesses of this Truth about outward concernments, one from another, so that they should not bee able, or wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to concur, or agree, about that which is their great and main concernment, <hi>viz. The testimonie of Jesus.</hi> Secondly, by making them, through the neglect of their main concernment, <hi>(viz.</hi> the testimonie of the life and death, and Resurrection of <hi>Jesus,</hi> and of the Covenant of Peace, between God and us in him) to becom contemptible to the world; and through their medling with heterogene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al concernments of the world, to becom an eie-sore, and an object of jealousie to the secular Powers. Thirdly, by ingaging them into parties about State-affairs, to make them the ring-leaders of designs, or at least, to bee counted such (which is almost all one, as to his end) that the guilt of publick evils, and miscarriages, may bee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted unto them more then to others. Seeing (I saie) these were Satan's aims; I proposed this Method for us, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in som conference, tending to prevent the evils, and to settle us in an agreement about future proceedings.</p>
               <p>First, that wee should consider and resolv, how to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed unanimously, as one man, by undoubted scriptural Rules, in opposing fundamental Heresies, and upholding the fundamental truths of Christianitie, and the practice of godliness.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that wee should consider and resolv, how to own unanimously, and upon what undeniable grounds, to profess our beeing in the Ministerie; what to own
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58502:19"/> therein, as <hi>jure Divino;</hi> and what to acknowledg to bee but prudential.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that wee should consider and resolv, how to maintein the Engagement which wee lie under, by reason of the National Oath, and Covenant; what therein, as to us, in these times is altered; and what for ever is unaltera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to bee prosecuted.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, and lastly, that wee should consider, and predetermine, in case a new Engagement bee offered (for when I made these proposals to som, the Engagement was not yet voted) by what Rules wee ought to walk; to bee able to finde out the inoffensive waie of doing our dutie towards all, aswel Superiors as equals.</p>
               <p>These proposals were made to more then one or two, as preparatives to bring on an agreement, between the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senting godlie parties about Church-Government, and Discipline: that the dore which their division hath open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to let in all manner of disorderlines, in the profession of Religion, might bee stop't at last, and Satan lose the advantages which hee hath gotten thereby against us: but they were not hearkned unto: either, becaus I was look't upon as a stranger; or as a subtil man that served State<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ends, for som advantage to my self, and made this propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal a cloak onely to som further design; or becaus men's spirits were straightned, and prepossessed with particular apprehensions, and could not bee raised to an impartial contemplation of that which was truly publick, and then seasonable to bee don. But if these matters had then been thought upon, or could yet bee determined, so, as to cleer our judgments to one another; and to all the world, in that which concern's our dutie in our sphere of acting; without reflecting upon others, in that whereof wee are not made their judges; there would not bee so much ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mositie, and so manie mistakes, and destructive jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies, as now are amongst us; nor could wee bee so much in the dark, and under so manie scruples, and snares of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science as now wee do lie, for want of following this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of proceeding in determining the matters, whereof
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:58502:19"/> wee are made competent judges; for if wee had judged these matters by the Rules and Principles, wherein wee are fully agreed; or did yet exercise our selvs by the right use of these Rules and Principles, to judg our own actions in these matters, rather then other men's failings from their duties, wherein to us they are not accountable, wee would finde light to walk in these occasions without doubting; and see caus, to cast off the scruples which are raised upon the grounds before mentioned; as beeing matters whereof wee are not competent judges, and without the considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of which, our actings relating to the publick, may, and ought to bee regulated: and can bee regulated by the rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal and conscionable disquirie of the forenamed propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sals; which I have offered now unto you, as formerly to others, that you may see, that I am so far from restraining my brethren to bee competent judges of their own actings; that it hath been one of my designs, to bring them to a regular waie of judging thereof; that they might not walk doubtfully therein, as now they do.</p>
               <p>Those things beeing thus at large premised to what I am about to saie, for the resolving of your third scruple; I shall intreat you to consider, whether the former scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, concerning the alteration of the government against the oath of Allegiance, taken by those that did alter it; is not raised in us, by a judicature of State-matters, whereof you confess us not to bee competent judges: and if no competent judges, then (I saie) no judges at all; to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine matters with reference to our conscience, to saie, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they have don well or ill; but I must saie they stand or fall, to their own master in this business of the alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Government; I may, as a rational man, and a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject concerned in point of Common-welfare, look upon their actions in altering the government, with the eie and judgment of discretion, to discern what they saie, and what they do for the alteration: but when I am gon to the utmost extent of my discerning facultie, yet I must make none other definition, but such as keep's my conscience free from beeing obliged, to give a sentence which will
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:58502:20"/> scruple mee in the points of dutie towards them. If they saie that the judicature of all the King's actions doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long unto them, as they are the Representatives and Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stees of a free Nation, which hee was to govern by Laws, which they shall chuse, and not by will; and that hee for raising war against them, and refusing to give an account of his actions, (to those whom they appointed as judges in their name, to call him to an account of treasonable en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprises) hath been deprived of the government where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with hee was intrusted, and of his life, and that, as in Cases of Treason, by the Law of nature, and of Nations, the prerogative which hee lost for himself, was also for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited for his posteritie; and that their proceedings against him, and those that would support him in his pretended in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest of absoluteness, above Parlaments, or of indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie from them; are such as they will answer to God for; and as they will undertake to shew their grounds of, before all the world, and if according to these sayings, they do make Laws, to settle us in another relation one to another, and under themselvs (that is under the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant government of Representatives) without a King, and Hous of Lords; If (I saie) I can clearly discern, that they saie, and do all this, without turbulencie of spirit, in a waie of counsel, rationally and orderly behaving themselvs; looking aswel to God, as to men, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing according to their light, a willingness to keep a good conscience towards both, at all times, if (again I saie) when I use the judgment of discretion, I finde things thus constituted with them, what shall I saie other, but that this thing is of God; that his will must bee don in earth as in heaven; that power belongeth unto him, and that hee exalteth over the Kingdoms of men, whomsoë<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hee pleaseth: If I finde them by these Principles, and actings in their places of trust over mee, to intend order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie courses; and minde the things belonging to common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safetie; I cannot see what warrant I have to disown them to bee of God. Sure I am, except God had disowned the King's exercise of power, and blasted his Counsels,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:58502:20"/> and given him up to these men, to bee judged by them, as hee was, they could have don nothing unto him; if then God hath disowned him, and owned these in the sight of all the world, and doth intrust them with the management of all publick affairs; who am I, to take upon mee to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own them in the places wherewith they are actually pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessed, except I had a commission from him, to let them see, that either their Principles of acting are not allowed by him, or that their actings are not according to their Principles? but if I am not inabled to do either of these two; but rather am convicted that the Principles, which they have taken up, are of God in them; and that their actings by these Principles, with Counsel and courage, by a professed confidence in him, have been carried on in an orderlie cours to this issue by his Providence; then I must own them thus far to bee of God; and look upon them as instruments in his hand; to bring about this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of affairs, to fulfil his judgments one waie; his mercies another waie, and both waies his determined Counsel, which hath concluded mee under their power, and doth subordinate mee in my calling under their act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, to do my dutie without grudging, or murmuring, without disputing and scrupulositie, beeing harmless and blameless in my waie, as it becometh a child of God, hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth the word of life and light, as the rule of my walking.</p>
               <p>Thus then I conclude upon these grounds; that if I do own them in their places by anie dutisul actings in my calling, I do not sin; but rather fulfil that which I am bound to think (according to the judgment of discretion concerning them; and the definitive judgment of dutie in Christianitie concerning my self) is the will of God, and the work of my present calling; for if I by doing my dutie, and having none other aim, but to act within my sphere; do eventually set them up, and own them in their places; I must attribute that unto God's ordering of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; and leav the effect thereof unto him; but if I should think, that becaus I suppose such an event will follow,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:58502:21"/> that therefore I must not intend my present dutie; I saie if I should think thus; then I walk not in simplicitie, but according to the wisdom of this world; and I prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine in my thoughts, the events which are onely in God's hands; and I follow not a cleer and universal rule in my actings; but the rule of a design, which I have framed to my self, upon a conjectural apprehension of som event, which I would not have com to pass; for in effect, it is as much as if I had said thus; I do not see that these men are of God; and becaus I see it not; <q>I will do nothing, no not the best duties of my present calling, lest by doing that which is my dutie, I seem to own them, and lest it may tend to confirm them in their places:</q> which in my apprehension would bee to drive a design against the present powers, by a sinful neglect of doing my dutie to the publick: which how it can bee warrantable in Christianitie, I know not.</p>
               <p>The last part of the third scruple, is an aggravation of the doubt; When you saie: <hi>besides by subscribing, they do not onely own the power, but also the imposing of the ingagement; (if not directly, yet indirectly) which they cannot see how it agree's with the Rule, that require's higher powers should bee a terror to evil, not to the good, as by this means they are.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If in the first part of the scruple, when you said, that though private men bee no competent judges of State-matters, yet they are competent judges of their own actions; you meant by their own actions, their owning or disowning the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent power, <hi>viz.</hi> that they were to judg competently, whether the present power was to bee owned or disowned by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selvs, yea, or no; I shall in som sens grant this; as thus. First, that they were definitively to determine with themselvs, what everie private man is bound to do, as a Christian to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the present powers, to own them or disown them, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Rule of obedience, prescribed by God in the word. Secondly, that they were also definitively to determine with themselvs, what the present powers are, that are actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally over them, who are obedientially to bee owned or disowned. In these two cases it is cleer, that everie man
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:58502:21"/> must bee allowed to judg, who is actually over him in power, and by what Rule of obedience hee ought to walk under him, as owning him in his place; but if the sens bee this, that everie man is competently to judg his own actions, in respect of the confequence which they may have, towards the owning, or the disowning of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent powers; and accordingly as hee shall see caus, to own them or disown them, that hee may act or not act, as hee shall think his action conducing to one or the other end; so that the aim of owning or of disowning shall becom the measure of the rectitude of his actions: if (I saie) this bee the meaning of those words, then I must denie anie man to bee a competent judg of his own actions: for no man is to judg of the rectitude, or unrighteousness of his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by the eventualitie thereof, which hee may propose unto himself will follow: for in this sens I take the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet's words: <hi>O Lord! I know that the waie of man is not in</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 10. 23.</note>
                  <hi>himself; if is not in man that walketh to direct his steps.</hi> This is true, as to the event; no man can direct anie thing which hee doth to anie event; and therefore hee is to measure no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by the eventualitie thereof, in his own apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, but hee is bound to measure it by a Rule and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, and in this sens the contrarie is true, <hi>viz.</hi> It is in man that walketh to direct his steps, els this promise would bee in vain: <hi>Hee that ordereth his conversation aright, shall see the salvation of God,</hi> Psal. 50. 23. and the Commandement; <hi>See that yee walk circumspectly,</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>not as fools, but as wise,</hi> Ephes. 5. 15. it is therefore in a man as his dutie, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect his steps by a rule, but it is not in himself at all to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect his steps to anie event whatsoëver; for it is said, that <hi>man's goings are of the Lord; how can a man then understand his own waies,</hi> Prov. 20. 24. God's providence doth order all men's goings to his secret ends, and by his own counsel to determined effects; therefore it is not possible for a man to understand the eventual tendencie of his own waie; and if it is not possible for him to understand this, then it is not lawful for him to measure, or judg the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of his action by this; now if I do not mistake the matter and meaning of this scruple, it seem's first to assert
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:58502:22"/> that for them, to own the present powers to bee of God, is a sin; upon this account; becaus it is doubtful to them upon the grounds before mentioned: (which were pure State-considerations) and <hi>what is not of faith is sin; ergò</hi> they may do nothing, which in their judgment tend's to own them as of God; for although they are no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent judges of State-matters, yet they are competent judges of their own actions; and if they judg their own actions to bee an owning of them, as of God: then to them, to do these actions is a sin; and consequently, they must abstain from them, although in themselvs the actions bee never so good; onely becaus they judg them to have a tendencie eventually to speak, and own such a thing, whereof they doubt, and which they would not have them to speak; therefore they think themselvs bound in conscience to abstain from them, which I think is a great mistake, as already hath been shewed; and upon this mistake, <hi>the second part of the scruple</hi> assert's, that in the act of subscribing, there is more sin then in other obediential Acts: upon this account, becaus it doth tend, not onely to own the present power; but also the imposing of the Engagement, at least indirectly. Now saie you, they may do nothing, either directly, or indirectly, which may own the imposing of the Engagement; and why? becaus, saie you, they cannot see how the Engagement agree's with the rule that require's higher powers should bee a terror to the evil, not to the good; as by this means they are. If you had said, becaus they cannot see anie thing required in the Engagement, to bee agreeable to the rule of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian's walking, or the dutie of Subjects to the higher powers, the reason would have been to my judgment sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactorie; and wee must have examined the nature of the things required in the Engagement; to know whether they were inconsistent with the rules of Christianitie, and the Dutie of Subjects; and upon the discoverie of what is meant by beeing true and faithful to the Common-wealth, as it is now established, without a King and Hous of Lords wee might have com to som conclusion; for if there
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:58502:22"/> had been found in these words a sens consistent with those rules, and this Dutie; then the scruple could have been resolved: and the Conscience setled; but now this cannot bee don; becaus the Scruple is not fixed upon the material part of the Engagement; which is our private concernment, to see what wee thereby are obliged to do; and so accordingly to resolv to bee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged or not to bee engaged thereunto: but it is fixed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Construction which is made of the intention of the higher powers in proposing the engagement, and upon the disagreement of that which they do, by the proposall of the engagement, with that which the rule of their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling doth require of them. Now to mee a scruple so fixed is wholly to be rejected: becaus I finde it not lawful for mee to make my self a Judg either of their intentions; or of their particular actings, how agreeable they are with the rules of their calling, I may tell them as well as other men what their intentions ought to bee, and how they should take heed to the rule of their Calling; this I may, and ought to do in these; but in <hi>Hypothesi</hi> to judg posi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively what their intentions are (except I were one of their Counsel) and what their actings are in order to a rule (except I were made acquainted with all the Circumstances of their state) is a thing which I dare not undertake; far less then may I upon the supposal of such a judgement con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their intentions or actings, be obliged to suspend mine own resolution from doing the duties of my calling, or scruple my Conscience about acting things lawfull in my place. I dare not say then, that by the means of the engagement, they either intend to bee, or are a terror to the good, and not to the evill, contrary to the rule given by God to higher powers. But I look upon the imposing of it with the judgement of discretion, to bee a thing, which they think absolutely necessarie for common safetie; and therefore press with a severe penaltie: which I must leav them to answer for, if there be no such necessitie; but in the definitive judgment of Christianitie, as the engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment relat's to mee, I find a Dutie in it; whereunto I
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:58502:23"/> am required to oblige my self; which in Conscience I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not refuse to do; and so Subscribe it with a full purpose to perform the Dutie which the law of Christianitie and of a good Subject doth require. What Consequences may follow upon, and what interpretations others may make of this my action, I am not sollicitous of, I look to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing further then to the warrantableness of that which I do at present. For as in reason, <hi>Ex vero nîl nisi verum:</hi> So in moralitie and Christianitie <hi>Ex bono nîl nisi bonum sequitur per se.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for matters of offence (the subject of your fourth Scruple) which may follow <hi>per accidens</hi> upon lawful acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in som Cases they are unavoidable; for if I think I am in Conscience bound to do somthing as a Dutie, and another bee so weak as to bee offended at mee for doing it, how can this offence bee avoided? must I neglect a dutie, and wound mine own conscience, becaus another is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at that which I do? If hee bee so unreasonable as not to let mee have the libertie to keep a good Conscience; in following the dictates thereof for my self; must I bee so foolish as to give up the use of my libertie to his weakness? In matters of indifferencie where I may chuse to do, or not to do; and where nothing else com's in competition, but the meer pleasing of my self; with the danger of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasing another; there I am bound not to pleas my self, but another to his edification: nay although it may bee to my great bodilie disadvantage, I must bear it, rather then my brother should have anie spiritual disadvantage by mee; for there is no proportion between a bodilie and spiritual inconveniencie; but in Case the inconveniencie which I do incur, is not at all bodilie, but spiritual; no law of Charitie can oblige mee to undergo it; for no man can bee pleasured or edified by my spiritual disadvantage, this is to shew why none ought to bee offended at mee for doing that which I think is my Dutie. And why if anie bee offended, I nevertheless must own that which I have don and let them know, that the offence is not given, but unjustly taken. But your 4<seg rend="sup">th</seg> Scruple run's upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:58502:23"/> strain of offences, and tend's to another scope, which is to plead for the Non-subscribes under the Notion of weak Brethren, whom wee are bid not to offend. Their weakness is to think that unlawful (which perhaps is lawful) becaus it may seem contrarie to a rule of the word. As in this Case of the engagement; the rule of Oaths and promises seem's to bee violated; which a man is bound to keep though to his hurt.</p>
               <p>For mine own part, I do heartily wish and praie to God that the spirit of Christian compassion may bee amongst us; and that the Non-subscribers may not onely bee look't upon by the imposers and subscribers, as weak brethren and those that ought to bee dealt tenderly withall; but that also they may behave themselvs so that all may have Caus, and chiefly the imposers of the engagement, to think that it is rather through weaknes and tendernes of Conscience indeed, then through som other inclination that they refuse to subscribe. For I must tell you ingenuous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that it is as hard a task as ever I have medled withall, to make som of the imposers of the engagement beleev, that it is more out of tendernes of Conscience, then out of a design that most men contradict the Subscription of the engagement: I truly beleev it, to bee that scruple which you allege in most of the Ministers, if not in all that are Godlie; but the violence and cross actings of som doth bring an invincible prejudice against all.</p>
               <p>As for these that are in places of power to provide for common safetie, they saie to this: that it is a matter of absolute necessitie to press the settlement of som fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal relation in the Common-wealth between the members thereof; and therefore they cannot in Conscience neglect their trust, but must indispensably endevor the preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the publick by this means; and if their Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence bee as strongly engaged one waie, as the other's are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother way; no Cours is in view, but a friendlie treatie to prevent the inconveniencie of mutual offences, and further breaches; that mistakes may bee removed and differences re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled: which I shall not ceas to praie for to God and Solicite towards men.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:58502:24"/>
               <p> The last Scruple, or rather asspersion of yours in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to what I had said in my last, I shall not contradict; for I willingly confess, that in doubtful matters and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult cases the spirits of Prophets should bee subject unto the Prophets: only admit of the limitation which I did add in my former expression; that no Church, far less a forreign Church, ought to bee made a Judg of Civil Sanctions in a state. But that the spirits of Prophets ought to bee Subject to the Prophets, is one of the great fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentals which I mainly press as a means to rectifie our endles disputes: nor is anie man more avers from enthusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asticall fancies then I am; yet I am not led by any impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite faith or resignation of my judgement to other men so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions: but I seek light from them; and when I find that upon Conference I can neither bring them to my sens, nor they mee by Conviction of my Judgement to their's, I think it my Dutie to be silent, and to suspect mine own opinion as that which may bee wrong, although I cannot see it to bee so.</p>
               <p>You may perceiv by the largeness of my discours upon the heads of these Scruples that my spirit is not straitned in Love towards the Brethren that desire som help; which as I said at first, God only can give, who is the Father of lights and of all good gifts; and if wee laie one another's Cases to heart with tendernes and meeknes, and cal upon him one for another, wee may hope that hee will bless our gifts for mutual advantage. The secrecie and cautiousnes which is requisit in this business you may assure your self of, with all Confidence; as also of all other duties and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of love, which in the fear of God may bee exspected from</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your affectionate Brother in Christ</hi>
                     <lb/> JOHN DVRIE.</signed>
                  <lb/>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>St James</hi>
                     <lb/>
                     <date>
                        <hi>April</hi> 4. 1650.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:58502:24"/>
                  <head>Postscript.</head>
                  <p>YOur's came to my hand on the 28. <hi>March,</hi> the next daie I begun to answer it, but I was obliged to go out of the town the same daie, towards night, which inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted my proceeding for a few daies, and occasioned a delaie, which I would not have you to impute to anie unwillingness to serv you; but the chief intent of this <hi>Postscript,</hi> is now not to excuse this slow return; but to make som addition to that, which may bee your satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction concerning the first scruple. For since I wrote that which here is said, concerning the Question you make; <hi>what I mean by that known dutie which I often urge;</hi> I have light upon a place in the reproposals, to which you (I make no doubt) allude. It is in <hi>pag.</hi> 10. 11. and there my meaning is, to call that a cleer and known du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which in the second Section of the Humble Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sals is confessed, to bee from <hi>the light of nature,</hi> from <hi>the judgment of the Learned,</hi> from the <hi>practice of Christians in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ages,</hi> from <hi>their own Principles,</hi> and from their <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer engagements consonant to the will of God;</hi> viz. <hi>that they should live quietly and peaceably in their places and callings, sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting to such things as are imposed upon, or required of them, by the powers which are in actual possession, beeing in themselvs lawful and necessarie, to the preservation of our selvs and others: which may bee don</hi> (saie they) <hi>without disputing the right and title of those that are in place.</hi> To do this, (which the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble proposals themselvs thus acknowledg upon so manie grounds, to bee a dutie of Subjects towards Superiors, who have none other cleer title, but actual possession) I do there call the cleer and known dutie, which the Engagement doth require, which therefore ought not to bee scrupled at, by those who are willing to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form this dutie. For if it bee freely acknowledged up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on so manie cleer grounds, that the powers who are in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:58502:25"/> actual possession without inquiring into their title, should bee obeied in things just, and necessarie for common pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation; then there is no caus for anie man to scruple at the Engagement; for the Engagement by the cleer sens of the words, and the whole tenor of the Act, by which it is imposed, doth require nothing more then in this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment is expressed to bee a Dutie, which I in my Reproposals call <hi>cleer,</hi> becaus the proposals allege so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie grounds to evidence it; and I call it <hi>known,</hi> becaus they themselvs so fully confess it Besides the former delaie, there hath been another step in the slow transcription of these former sheets: that I might have a copie of them by mee; for my man that copied them out, hath not the hand of a readie writer; yet I hope no time is lost, and I assure you, if anie bee, it is not willingly.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your brother and servant<lb/> in the Gospel,</hi>
                        <lb/> JOHN DURIE.</signed>
                     <lb/>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>St James's</hi>
                        <date>this 9<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
                           <lb/>
                           <hi>April</hi> 1650.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="letter">
               <head>The third Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Reverend and worthie Sir!</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Must still return you manie thanks, and acknowledg my self much obliged to you, that you are readie to bestow such unwearied pains, in performing an office of love to your weak brethren: you needed not to have spoken anie thing touching the long staie of your Letter; for I had reason to wonder rather it came so soon, considering you had taken such pains in it; mine had been return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned sooner to you, but that I desired som friends might first have a sight of yours, that I might know their thoughts about it: for my self I may truly saie, that I have caus to bless God for your labors, and from that light which I have received from them; som of my good friends are now satisfied in the business; others,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:58502:25"/> who are truly godlie still stick fast in their former doubts, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not see their waie cleer before them. I finde it to bee true which you mentioned, namely, that it is not in the power of man, but a priviledg belonging to God alone, to bee able to satisfie the scruples of a tender conscience: It is hee that sit's (as it were) at the stern of everie man's understanding, and can steer it which waie hee pleaseth; so as that argument which seem's to bee verie weightie to one man, to another seem's to have little strength in it: that distinction which seem's to one verie fit for cleering of knottie scruples, doth seem to another to have little soliditie in it: so that if wee will not violate the rule of love, wee must have the patience to permit others to bee of a differing judgment from us in doubtful things, and yet like them never the wors, when their liking stand's as strongly to the best things as our own. Give mee leav therefore to commend it to you, as a principal office of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian charitie, to do what lie's in you to take off the thoughts of such as are in place (whom you have anie interest in) from that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable apprehension, that such who refuse the ingagement, do it not out of weakness, but wilfulness: for such a pervers prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple as this put on the Prelates in times past, to the violent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuting of pious Non-conformists becaus (they having said much in defence of superstitious ceremonies) they took it as granted, that such as still stumbled at them must needs do it out of obstinacie, and peevishness, and not out of true tenderness; and when anie shall have throughly digested this dangerous principle, they may easily bee carried forward to the exercise of much violence, against the dear servants of God, whom they ought to cherish as their own chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Give mee leav briefly to tell you what it is, that som godlie men stick at.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>First,</hi> It beeing taken as granted, that King and Lords, and all the Privileges of Parlament must bee subordinate to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick safetie, yet who must bee judges? what make's most for the publick safetie, but the major part of our representatives, who were chosen for that purpose, who when the Hous was full and free, (as before I told you) declared it to bee most for the publick safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, to agree with the King upon the best terms they could, and that there should bee still a continuance both of him, and the Hous of Lords.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:58502:26"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is objected, that none are thought now competent judges of those actions, which have been don by such who are in pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, but themselvs, who are the autors of them, which crosseth the usual rule, (<hi>vid.</hi> that no man is a competent judg of his own actions) and also their former practice; for heretofore, both King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament, in manie of their Declarations, did appeal to the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the people, to determine whether of their proceedings did most agree to the preservation of Religion, and the libertie of the Subject, and accordingly to side with them, or against them; and now the whole Kingdom, Nobilitie, Gentrie, Divines, Lawyers, and men of all ranks and orders, must bee bound up to yield a blinde obedience to a few men, that have gotten the Government into their hands, without their consent, and do exercise it in a far more ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrarie waie, then ever the King himself did.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It make's them much doubt, whether those in power will bee real for Religion or not, becaus they suffer such abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble blasphemies to break forth in divers parts of the Kingdom, and no condign punishment is exercised against the autors of them; there beeing a generation of men risen up in manie places, who openly profess themselvs to bee deified; and therefore that the most hideous cursing and swearing, beastlie drunkenness, or foul uncleanness are things not evil in them, becaus they are the actions of God: of whom they might bee as easily informed, and take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice (if they pleased) as they are of such who refuse the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> They still stick at <hi>Romans</hi> 13. as not to bee under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood of usurped powers, on these grounds; <hi>First,</hi> if higher powers bee of God onely, by a common providence, though without a rule, this will make ill for the autoritie and credit of Magistracie; for then Magistrates should bee no more of God, then plagues, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mins, and other common calamities, all which com in a provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dential waie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> the powers here spoken of, are such as must not bee resisted, but usurpers may bee resisted as <hi>Athaliah</hi> was; these must bee maintained by paying of tribute; usurpers not so.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> these are said to bee ordained of God; but lawful power onely is God's Ordinance, not usurped power. Lawful Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates are, not onely ordained by a secret providence, (as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlie
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:58502:26"/> men are ordained to condemnation) but by his written word and sanction. The sons of <hi>Aaron</hi> had another manner of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, then <hi>Korah</hi> and his companie, though they took upon them to exercise the Priestlie office.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The Magistrate here spoken of, is the Minister of God, <hi>Ergò</hi> called of God to that service, as Ministers are to their work; hee is the Minister of God for the welfare of the people, usurpers not so; hee is to take vengeance on evil doers, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute wrath for God, <hi>Ergò,</hi> not by providence onely (as thievs, robbers, and forreign invaders) but by place and calling.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> by this reason, if Malignants, Levellers, Papists, or anie others should get to bee the strongest partie, wee must yield obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to them, as to the powers that are of God.</p>
               <p>Sir, I dare not desire you to clear these scruples, lest I should put you to more pains: but if your leasure will permit to do it, I shall bee thankful, and leav you to take what leasure you pleas. I am sorrie to hear that anie good men should refuse so fair, and rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal a waie of accommodation, as you tendred to them; yet I dare not censure them, becaus I am ignorant of their grounds: but (I suppose) if you had made the like motion to <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> N. N. M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> N. N.</hi> or som other of their temper, it would have been lovingly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terteined. Sir, I hope you shall not repent of your pains, if still you exercise more patience in seeking, how such a business may bee brought about: and I know you have often made use of that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise, wherein blessedness is pronounced to Peace-makers. Thus desiring our good God still to enlarge you with affections, and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities fit for making up these great breaches, that are still amongst us; I resign you to his mercie.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours most obliged in the<lb/> best bond of love.</signed>
                  <lb/>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>this</hi> 29<seg rend="sup">th</seg>. <hi>of April</hi>
                        <lb/> 1650.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="answer">
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:58502:27"/>
               <p> and full, that it was most for publick safetie to agree with the King upon the best terms they could, and that there should bee still a continuance both of him and of the Hous of Lords.</p>
               <p>Suppose this to bee so, what then? then (say they) it follow's that the present constitution of affairs (being contrarie to that which the major part of the hous then declared) is not for publick safetie; and if this constituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doth not tend to publick safetie, then it follow's that the engagement by which it is confirmed ought not to bee entred into; for no man should oblige himself to that which is contrarie to publick safetie. This I conceiv is the whole strength of the Scruple as it may lie in their conception.</p>
               <p>But I shall freely tell you that with mee it hath no weight at all, as to engage my Conscience in the busines; as to take mee off from taking the Engagement, for manie things are here presupposed which are to mee uncertain; and though they bee granted to bee true, yet they reach not at all to put an obligation upon my Conscience to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stain from the engagement as now it is offered.</p>
               <p>They presuppose here that in a state of War aswel as in a peaceable constitution of affairs whatsoëver is determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and allowed by a major part is most for publick safetie which is to mee a very doubtful assertion. Wee finde that matters have been carried on all along in both Kingdoms rather by a Minor then by a Major part of the Nation; and if this rule should be taken up universally; <hi>Whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ëver the Major part doth is best don; and most agreeable to Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice in all things;</hi> it will go ill with the people of God in the world; and the narrow waie, with the few that walk in it, will not bee justified: this rule therefore is not in all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses and at all times to bee admitted; but it must needs ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of some restriction, whereby in matters of extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie concernment, a partie which is most considerable, though fewer, may dissent from a partie which is less considerable, though more in number. Wee see then that this first presupposal whereupon the whole Scruple is grounded is not sound.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:58502:27"/>
               <p> Besides this presupposal, there is this also intimated in the Scruple, that what formerly was declared to bee most for publick safetie, must now also be judged to bee so; as if the several Emergencies in state affairs could not give caus to alter justly their opinions concerning the waie of publick safetie.</p>
               <p>Again a third presupposal is implied in this Scruple viz. That the hous is not now free and full as then it was; which how I can take upon mee to assert I know not, seeing they who are onelie competent Judges of their own freedom, do vote themselvs to bee free; and seeing it is an undoubted fundamental law of the Parlamentarie Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution that fortie Members regularly met are a full Hous to all intents and purposes, aswel as four-hundred: now it is known that the Hous was never less then fortie: therefore it hath alwaies been full: and a full Hous may repeal it's own acts upon Emergencies as it seeth caus.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, it is not only presupposed, but expresly as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serted, that the Hous declared that is was most for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick safetie to agree with the King on the best terms they could, and that there should bee stil a continuance of Him and of the Hous of Lords; Truly I beleev that times were, when Votes did pass in the Hous to this effect, though not in those terms; which is cleer by several pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Declarations importing no less; but I beleev also that upon new Emergencies their sens of agreeing did alter, and that since the King was at <hi>Holdenbie,</hi> and the Armie took him into their custodie, and that hee stil refused to yield to their Propositions, their sens of publick safetie did much varie, from what you here express it was, as was manifest by the votes of <hi>Non-addresses;</hi> and it is certain, that this which is alleged was not the vote <hi>in terminis;</hi> for which the Members were separated from the Hous: that Vote was <hi>in terminis,</hi> this; <hi>That the Answers of the King to the Propositions of both Houses, were a ground for the Hous to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed upon, for the settlement of the Peace of the Kingdom.</hi> This was the fatal dividing Vote, which in the sens of som, I believ, did tend to that, which you saie the Hous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:58502:28"/> but in the sens of others, it might tend to settle the peace of the Kingdom without him. Som thought it was best to agree with the King upon anie terms whatsoë<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, to carrie on a design: but others thought it more safe, not to admit of the terms which hee offered, for fear of that design.</p>
               <p>It appear's by that which is fallen out, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the partie most numerous did vote in the first, yet the partie most considerable voted in the last sens, and which of these two did vote most wisely and justly; if I should take upon mee to determine, who am without dores, and not conscious to circumstances of State, nor intrusted with the management of publick affairs, it would in mine own judgment bee a very great presumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and contrarie to the Rule, by which I walk in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scionable submission to superior powers; for I make this my Rule, that my conscience is obliged to nothing, but to judg of mine own waies, how they may, within my calling bee made answerable to the will of God, by the Rules which hee hath given mee. Now I said, no Rule given by him to mee in my calling, which doth oblige mee to bee a definitive judg of these matters; so as to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten them upon my conscience, that except I bee able to determine them, I may take no rest, nor intend the main duties of my profession. Nay, I finde a contrarie cleer Rule. <hi>That I must not bee a busie bodie in other men's affairs;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 15. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 19. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. 1. <hi>Jude</hi> 3. 8.</note>
                  <hi>That beeing free from all, I must becom a servant to all, in that which is for edification; I must bee subject to superior powers, and not speak evil of Dignities;</hi> and that I must not suffer my conscience to <hi>bee brought under the power of</hi> worldlie and <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 12. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 21, 22.</note> outward concernments: for I am told that <hi>all things are mine,</hi> therefore <hi>I must not bee brought under the power of anie thing,</hi> but beeing <hi>bought with a price by the Lord, I must not bee</hi> (as to conscience) <hi>a servant of men;</hi> from which Rules <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 23, 24.</note> I infer this, that, although I suppose all that is alleged, to bee so, as it is alleged; and all the presupposals to bee undoubted and certain, yet they must not reach, and com within mee so far; as to becom a scruple to my consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence;
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:58502:28"/> and to make no doubt, whether yea or no, I should behave my self as a Subject, towards those that are my supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors; obeying Magistrates readily in everie good work, not speaking evil of them, nor brawling against them; but shewing all gentleness and meekness, both to them, and to all men, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. 1, 2. I leav then the judicature of publick safetie to those that are in publick places: I praie to God for them; that they may bee inabled to judg aright, and to see their waie before them, and whether they do right or wrong in particular matters; I leav the judgment thereof unto God, and to their conscience; and look onely to mine own walking in my private sphere, to bee without blame, and to hold forth the word of life, and let the changes bee, what ever they will or may bee, in the states of this world, they shall no more trouble mee, if I remain my self, then the changes of the air, when the weather is somtimes fair, and somtimes foul: the storm that bloweth over my head shall not make mee stand still in the high waie, nor lie down in the puddle, not going forward till the journies end; as I am afraid, manie who are angrie at the changes of the times, beeing of a sullen humor, are readie to do, becaus they cannot get their wills; but I believ not that anie of your friends are such: yet I cannot saie, that all godlie men are free from the snare of such a distemper.</p>
               <p>The second scruple is this; that, <hi>although no man can bee a judg in his own caus, and that although heretofore, both King and Parliament did appeal to the judgment of the people, to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine whether of their proceedings did most agree, to the preserva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Religion and Libertie, yet none are now thought compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent judges of those actions, which have been don by such who are in power, but themselvs; so that now all men are bound up, to yield a blinde obedience to those who have gotten the Government into their hands; and exercise it in an arbitrarie waie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I saie, suppose all this be so, what then? then (saie your friends) the Engagement ought not to bee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into, by which they will bee established in the use of this power: and this I take to bee the whole strength of this scruple also.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:58502:29"/>
               <p> But hereunto I saie, that I dare not take upon mee, to censure them, so as your friends do in this scruple; and although the accusations which are alleged, should bee made out, to bee such crimes as they would make them to bee; and that I should see no plea left for them, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they might justifie themselvs; yet the consequence which your friends make thereupon, would not follow as to my conscience: for suppose the matters alleged to bee as ill, and their proceedings as irrational as may bee, and that they abuse their power, as is alleged; yet I saie, that it is not warrantable for mee to refuse the Engagement: if it require in my judgment, a thing in it self good, and lawful to bee don for common safetie; for the supposed faultineses of these men in their places; (where of private men are not judges over them) cannot warrant mee to refuse the performance of a cleer and known dutie towards the publick in my place, which they may require of mee.</p>
               <p>But your friends will saie perhaps to this: but if your entering into the Engagement will establish them in the power which they abuse, how can you do it with a good conscience? I answer, that whatever is a cleer matter of dutie, ought for conscience sake to bee intended for it self without scrupling the event: becaus the future acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental effects, and contingent events of humane actions are wholly in God's hand; nor can I know whether my taking of the Engagement shall establish them in the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, which they have or no: and if it doth, whiles I do nothing but my dutie, I must leav that to God. Your friends that argue thus; wee will not resolv to bee <hi>true and faithful to the Common-wealth, as it is now esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished without a King and Hous of Lords,</hi> becaus, if wee do this, these men will bee confirmed in the places wherein they are, do not in this matter guid their reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution by a rule, but by a conjectural interest, and the forecast of som event, which they would, or would not have to fall out, which is not to follow, but to prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine Providence, a thing in our thoughts no waies
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:58502:29"/> to bee allowed, and a thing which they condemn in others, and yet herein it's practised by themselvs: for when they refuse thus to do a dutie upon this account, becaus happily these men will thereby bee established; they seem to mee to intend to oppose, and contradict Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence alreadie determined; now whether Providence will establish these men, in the place whereof they are fully pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest, yea or no, is a thing that I am not to look after: I must leav that unto God, and intend nothing, but to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in everie present action a cleer Rule; and if God will confirm them in their places, by my doing my dutie, why should I take upon mee, or settle in my thoughts to grudg at it, or to hinder that event? Shall I predetermine God's Counsel? Can I saie to him they ought not to bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed? or shall I by the neglect of a dutie, endevor to cast down those whom hee hath set up? Is not this to follow them that seek for changes? wee may wish, and seek also for changes to the better; if by doing our dutie, wee have caus to conjecture that such a thing may fall out; but to the end that a change of publick affairs may fall out, to neglect a dutie is altogether unwarrantable; or to studie in hatred to som persons, to bring a change in the Government is that which is forbidden, as I suppose, in the <hi>Proverbs</hi> by <hi>Solomon;</hi> as for mine own part, I freely declare, that I did not seek for the abolishment of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Government; but since God hath brought it about in his own waie; I am bound to <hi>dequiesce,</hi> and as I sought not to bring matters to this state by a change; so I shall not seek to bring matters from it again, by a new change; but I must by the rule of my place and calling, as a private man, resolv to do my dutie, in the settlement or unsettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which God doth give, what ever it is: so then you see, that if I must guid my conscience by a Rule, I must not measure the righteousness of my actions by the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances of events, which I conjecture may follow there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, but by the precepts, which tell mee what is my dutie in my place at all times, <hi>in presenti, hic &amp; nunc;</hi> nor must I look to other men's actions, by the constructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:58502:30"/> which I, or others may make of them, but I must look unto mine own waie; that is, to that which God require's of mee, in my private station. This your friends seem not to do, when they argue thus: wee will not take the Engagement, becaus wee will not confirm, but rather disturb these men in their places: this to my understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is to make conscience depend upon a design, and not upon the observation of a rule, in reference to a present dutie; now I dare not fasten anie humane design upon my conscience, nor make my conscience subject to anie thing, but to a cleer Rule of God's word: therefore, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the argument were proposed unto mee thus: <hi>You must not take the Engagement, becaus the action required in it, is in it self unlawful to bee don, by you in your place;</hi> except (I saie) it were thus offered unto mee, I can see no just plea to pretend conscience in the business; if then nothing to my judgment bee required of mee, which is unlawful for mee to bee don, in my place and calling; I must bee so far from pretending conscience, for not engaging thereunto; that I dare not for conscience sake, but bee engaged heartily; by reason of the universal, and undeniable Rule, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1. <hi>Let all souls bee subject to the higher powers; becaus the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers that are, are of God;</hi> and again, vers 5. <hi>You must needs bee subject for conscience sake.</hi> Thus then my conscience is not to bee subjected to the consequence, which your friends make; but unto this Rule of the word; although I should grant, that the premises, upon which they infer it to bee true: but if, when I look upon the Premises in themselvs, and by the judgment of discretion, finde them to bee such, as may bee meer mistakes, and misrepresen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of things, or at least great uncertainties, which I ought not to take upon mee to determine, then I am abundautly cleered in the matter, that I ought not to bee scrupled at the things alleged, as they are; nor do I think, that your friends, if they understood themselvs rightly, would suffer their conscience to bee scrupled at such considerations as these are; for if the Question bee concerning the actions of these men that now govern,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:58502:30"/> whether anie can or may judg of them definitively, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides themselvs; the answer must bee, as I conceiv, that if they are the higher powers, from whom none can ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal; then it followeth undeniably, that none can, or may judg of their proceedings but themselvs. The su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme government; that is, the Law-making power (which no man looking upon them, can denie them to bee pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest off) cannot bee accountable unto anie, but unto God: and if you will make them judges of their own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, you must name som to bee over them, able to call them to an account: but if none such can bee found; then wee must understand this Rule, that no man is a competent Judg of his own actions, <hi>cum grano salis: viz.</hi> of a single man, <hi>viz.</hi> that none is to bee made the sole, and supreme judg of his own caus, and actions, but that hee ought to bee accountable thereof unto others, becaus no single man on earth, is either by the Law of nature, or by God's appointment made onely for himself, or to bee without doing service unto others; and therefore by other's, to whom hee is appointed to do service, hee may bee judged, and is bound to give them an account of his stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardship; but in case a state, or whole nation by it's repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentatives, which by it self is free, and depend's upon none but God, doth contract it self into a Bodie, to whom it doth intrust it's whole power; this Bodie can bee accountable unto none, but unto God; nevertheless, each member of the Bodie is accountable unto the whole; onely the whole, as long as it hath the power, cannot bee called to an account of their proceedings by anie; els there would bee a <hi>processus in infinitum,</hi> or this absurditie would follow, that the supreme power would bee subject to it's inferior, that is no supreme, which is, <hi>contradictio in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecto;</hi> it follow's then, that where a Nation doth intrust the supremacie of their power, so to anie societie of men, that they can do with it what they think good, there none can bee judges of their actions definitively but themselvs; els the judges and governors, which are actually supreme, would have Superiors over them, which is absurd. Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:58502:31"/> the Supremacie is in the collective Bodie of a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but actually it can bee no where, but in the represen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives of the whole; and so long as the trust of the whole is in their hands, so long they must bee allowed to bee sole judges of their proceedings.</p>
               <p>As for that which is said, that both King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment did appeal to the people's judgment, to determine, whether of their proceedings did agree most with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of Religion, and Libertle of the Subject; I grant they did so; but their meaning was not by so doing, to set up everie private man above themselvs, as a defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive judg of the whole matter; but onely to justifie their proceedings to the judgment of discretion, in everie man, that hee might for his own good, bee inclined to favor the caus, which should seem in his eies most just; from this appeal, of both King and Parliament to the people, may bee gathered by the waie; First, that all Superiors are som waie accountable to the bodie of the Nation, of their administrations, and of the Reasons of their proceedings. Secondly, that all particular men may take notice, by the judgment of discretion, of the proceedings of their Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors, to swaie their resolutions to a rational concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, or non-concurrence in things required of them in their places. Thirdly, that no Superiors ought to think themselvs so absolute, as not to bee bound, to declare the grounds of their actions, that they may bee understanding<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly weigned by their inferiors, for whose sake they ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage publick affairs. From these grounds then, let mee offer to your discretion, that which I think rational, and tending to Peace, that seeing the Trustees of the Nation have disagreed amongst themselvs, and those that had the supremacie of power in their hand, have determined mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, according to the abilitie which God gave them; it is lawful for mee in my place, to look upon matters so far, as I discern them, to make the best thereof; but it is not lawful, nor conscionable, for mee to judg definitively of their proceedings, to make the worst thereof.</p>
               <p>You see then, that I cannot in conscience charge these
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:58502:31"/> men, that have the Government in their hand, with that which your friends judg them guiltie of. <hi>viz.</hi> First, that all men are made to yield a blinde obedience unto them; I cannot saie so; for I see that they offer to all men, an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their proceedings, and that they have carried on their resolutions rationally, according to emergencies, and are not unwilling to shew the reasons of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, to such as enquire after the same. Secondly, that they have the Government without the people's con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent: I cannot saie so; for I believ, that all that are in place, were chosen to their places by the free consent of the people. Thirdly, that they exercise their power more arbitrarily then the King did, in som sens I cannot saie so, and yet in another sens I may saie so. I may not saie so in the sens that your friends mean it, who I suppose, make all arbitrarie power as in the King, so in them equally unlawful. I may not saie so; becaus I am not a judg, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of him, or of them in their particular actings, and yet again, I may saie, that I conceiv it lawful in them to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise an arbitrarie power, which was not lawful in the King to do, becaus their trust from the Bodie of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is above that, which was given to the King; and the whole power which hee had, did primarily belong un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, as they were representatives of the Nation, who upon emergencie, have seen caus to resume it; and of this they have given an account to the bodie collective; so then, although it is their right, as supreme in the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, to do things arbitrarily; yet I cannot saie, that they intend to rule without Law, as it was imagined the King intended, by opposing the Law-making power of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presentatives, or that they intend to oblige all men, to yield a blinde obedience; for where Laws are made, and accounts given of publick proceedings; there men cannot bee justly said to bee obliged, to yield a blinde obedience: and thus you see, wherefore I am not staggered, at the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond scruple of your friends.</p>
               <p>The third matter here proposed, is not a scruple, but a complaint, with a suspicious conjecture of their intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:58502:32"/> concerning Religion; that they seem not to bee willing to advance it, becaus they punish not blasphem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and sinners against the light of nature, so much as those that take not the Engagement; to this I shall saie; that it is my dutie to mourn, for the abominations com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted within <hi>Jerusalem;</hi> to praie to God for a remedie against them, to warn, and admonish those that are in place of them; to encourage them to do their dutie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the publick, and towards my self, by doing my dutie in all things good and lawful towards them; and when I have don this, I must leav the event unto God; but if I will take up jealousies against them, becaus everie thing which I would have don, in publick by them, is not don, as I would have it; and upon my private jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies, I licentiate my self, not to do my dutie in my place towards them, and make others rebellious against them; and in my heart depose them from their places; then I weaken their hands, and hinder them, what in mee lieth from doing even that, which I complain is not don by them; and so make my self accessarie to the guilt of that evil, which I laie unto their charge; and so, while's I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse them, of the neglect of their dutie, to the publick, I neglect mine own dutie, both to my self, and to them, and to the publick, and abstract them also from doing their's.</p>
               <p>The last matter here offered is the consideration of <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. where your friends saie, that it is not to bee under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood of usurped powers, and you give mee their grounds, why they think so?</p>
               <p>As for mine own part, I cannot call to minde, that any where I have said, nor do I remember, that ever I was of opinion to saie: that the place is to bee understood of usurped powers; but I conceiv, it is to bee understood indefinitely, of the powers which are in place, what ever they are, whether usurped or not; if they bee the higher powers; for the words which the Apostle doth use, signifie nothing els; but that which is proper to a supreme Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate, implying nothing, either of usurpation, or lawful election to the place; but onely of a beeing in it, of the ground
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:58502:32"/> beeing in it of the ground of that beeing, as it is from God, of the Acts proper to the beeing in the place, and of the ends of those acts; and the duties of Subjects to bee performed towards them in reference to all this. I saie not then that the Apostle doth intend to perswade us, to obeie usurped powers; but hee doth declare, what wee ought to do, as Christians in submission to the powers that are over us; that is, to those that bear Rule: for the words used by the Apostle are indefinite <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> vers 1. and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. vers 3. these denominations determine nothing concerning the matter of usurpation, or a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful calling to their places; they implie onely three things. <hi>Viz.</hi> First, the Notion of power, or force in <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Secondly the notion of eminencie, or superioritie pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessed, in <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Thirdly, the notion of acting above others, or before others, in <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. So then, the object of our submission is indefinitely the <hi>might,</hi> which is pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessed of the superioritie, which is above us: and doth act in a waie of Government over us. Of these mights, or mightie ones, the Apostle saith indefinitely, that none of them have their place of Superioritie, or their <hi>might</hi> but of God; and whatever superioritie or might is in bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is ordained of God so to bee, over those that are in subjection to it; and therefore none ought to resist the su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior powers, that are over them for Government, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caus the Governors, or Magistrates are not a terror to good works, but to the evil; and this I take to bee the cleer sens of vers 1, 2, 3. If then the Apostle speake's of Magistrates, or Magistracie indefinitely, not reflecting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the particular waie, how they enter upon their places; but onely upon the actual possession thereof: and in that respect will have us to look upon them, as such whom God appoint's to bee obeied in things that are good; I know not why wee should trouble our selvs further, then the Holie Ghost doth give us caus, by limiting and defin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the title and right of the powers, into lawful and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, with reference to their enterance therein, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to humane Laws and customs; whereof in all this
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:58502:33"/> Scripture there is no intimation at all; nor was it then, nor is it now possible, for private Christians (to whom the Apostle write's) to judg of the lawfulness of the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, of those that are in place, to the power which they have; but hee refer's them onely to that which was appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, and whereof none could pretend ignorance, <hi>viz.</hi> to the powers which were actually over them, to rule them; these then as such, are to bee respected as the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of our submission; and this is cleerly <hi>Calvin's</hi> minde, <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Instit. cap.</hi> 20. <hi>parag.</hi> 24. till the end; where hee make's the office of Magistracie to bee the thing to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected by all, although men com to the possession of it by means, and waies never so unjust, and do nothing less, then what become's their places; for the unjust acquisiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a place, although it is a sin in him, who com's un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justly by it; yet it derogate's nothing from that which is due to the place, that is, the office according to God's ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment; for the office is his ordinance, and hee will have all souls to bee subject to it, in good things: els wee set up Anarchie.</p>
               <p>Now if your friends will without prejudice look upon these things; they will perceiv, that higher powers and rulers are to bee look't upon onely, as men in the office of Magistrates, and as such, to bee obeied: and this beeing granted, it will follow, whatever their personal faults may bee, that yet, so long as they are in the office of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistracie, they are to bee submitted unto in all good things: whether then they are usurpers or no, that is not material to my conscience; this Apostolical Rule binde's mee to respect the ordinance of God, which is the Ruler in his Office; to him, as such, I owe submission, nor am I to judg of anie thing further. By all which you may see, how I shall answer your friend's objections, which tend to shew, that the higher powers in <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. cannot bee meant of usurped powers; that is, of men com to the place of Government, by waies of usurpation; I shall saie to this, that the Apostle doth not express anie thing at all of this, and therefore wee may not assert, that hee meant anie such
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:58502:33"/> thing; nor doth hee express anie thing to exclude usur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, from having the title of higher powers; but his words, to my understanding, are indefinitely appliable to all, that are in the Office of supreme power; whether they bee usurpers, or no: therefore it is not that which is to bee look't upon; but if they bee high and Ruling powers, they are to bee regarded, as the Apostle doth enjoin, and for the reasons hee doth allege.</p>
               <p>As for the Arguments brought in to shew that usur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of the higher power cannot bee included in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination, which the Apostle give's to Magistrates here, I conceiv them far short of which they intend to prove.</p>
               <p>To the first I shall saie, that God's providence can have no Rule but his will; and it is no incongruitie, to saie, that God hath but one rule of ordering all things; which is the Rule of Righteousness. Whether then hee appoint's plagues and famines; or blessings, and plentiful seasons; and whether hee give's good and bad Magistrates; usur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, or lawfully called ones; all is don by the same rule of common providence, which is God's just and holie will. Nor is this at all ill for the Autoritie and credit of Magistracie to bee thus appointed: for the highest autori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is the supremacie of God's will; whose wisdom saith, <hi>by mee Kings reign, and Princes decree Justice,</hi> Prov. 8. 15. and the <hi>most high ruleth in the Kingdom of men, and giveth it to whomsoever hee will, and setteth up over it the basest of men,</hi> Dan. 4. 17. I shall confess, that as to men by the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of natural societie, God hath setled Rules for Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and for men to bee placed in Government; and so the Autoritie and credit of Magistracie is built upon an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other <hi>basis,</hi> as to us, then, that which doth bring Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities and plagues upon us, which com immediately from common providence, but that this man come's to the Government, either conformably, or not conformably, to those humane Rules of election, is immediately from God; and no disparagement at all to the office, and the respect due unto it, becaus hee hath given express Rules, both
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:58502:34"/> in the word, and in the nature of man, by which it is to bee upheld amongst men; and herein the autoritie of Magistra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie is differenced from plagues and calamities, and not in the reference, which it hath to common Providence; for by commons Providence all things have but one Rule, God's righteous will in judgment and loving kindness.</p>
               <p>To the second, which saith, that <hi>the powers here spoken of, must not bee resisted,</hi> but (saie your friends) <hi>usurpers may bee resisted, as</hi> Athalia <hi>was, these must bee maintained by pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of tribute, usurpers not so.</hi> I saie, that it is not lawful for anie private man, to whom the Apostle write's to resist the higher powers over him, whether the persons bee usurpers or no; nor is hee to make himself a judg of usur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation; but hee is to bee subject to the powers, that are in place and rule: As for <hi>Athalia,</hi> shee was not resisted by anie private, but by publick autoritie; for <hi>Jehoiada</hi> the high Priest, and the <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> was a publick autoritie; and by the Law of Nature, beeing the King's Tutor and Protector, hee was autorized to depose and execute the usurper; as for the assertion, that lawful Magistrates must bee maintained by paying tribute, but usurpers not so; I saie, that the dutie of paying tribute is injoined to Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects towards Majestrates <hi>quâ</hi> Magistrates; and not <hi>quâ</hi> lawful Magistrates; and consequently, it is not lawful for anie to refuse tribute upon this ground, becaus hee doth judg him to bee an usurper, who doth demand it; if hee doth finde him, in the place and office of a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate, and if no law of nature, or Nations, or of God is contrarie to what is demanded; hee is bound to paie tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, as to a Magistrate indefinitely, without this, or that respect to his personal qualities.</p>
               <p>The third objection saith; that lawful power is onely God's ordinance, and not usurped. This is to beg the Question: for God's Providence doth order the acts of usurpation (in themselvs as to men unlawful) to a good end; and the Magistracie still remain's his ordinance, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though seated in an usurper; and the highest power of might, which none can have, but by his giving of it,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:58502:34"/> is his ordinance, although an usurper hath the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 19. 10, 11.</note> of it: Christ tel's <hi>Pilate,</hi> when hee spoke of his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er or might, to save or condemn him, that hee could do nothing in that kinde, except it were given him from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove; God for judgment, give's and appoint's power to bee in the hands of Tyrants: they manage it unjustly, and in due time are punished for it; yet that Supremacie of power, in their hand, doth not ceas to bee an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God. It is true, that the sons of <hi>Aaron</hi> had ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner of ordination, then <hi>Korah</hi> and his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie; for <hi>Korah</hi> and his companie were never permitted to have the Priesthood; but if God had not punished them, but permitted them upon the plea, which they used to have managed the Priesthood, aswel as the service of the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, and that they had been in a peaceable possession of the office, what respect would then have been due unto them is a doubt unto mee, which I am not able, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess suddenly to determine; for I finde that Christ in his daies, did respect the Autoritie of the High-Priest; although hee was but annual; and came into his place by another waie, then God at first appointed <hi>Aaron</hi> and his sons to that office; Briberie, faction and politick practices had brought the office of the High-Priest, to bee annual and changeable, in respect of the men that had it, who perhaps, in those daies could not bee excused from usurpation upon one another; and yet the office was to bee respected in their hand, and look't upon as God's Ordinance; the personal faults of men make not void the appointment of God.</p>
               <p>To the fourth I saie, that all men, whom God doth anie waie imploie, are in som sens his Ministers; the original word is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which is a servant; and whoëver hath the place of an officer under God, is rightly called his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant; and none can have it; but by som waie of calling from God himself, either ordinarie, or extraordinarie: it follow's not therefore, that usurpers may not bee cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led God's servants; <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> an usurper, is called <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 25. 9.</note> God's servant by the Prophet; hee that doth service, and is imploied by a master to do it, is a servant; all Tyrants
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:58502:35"/> in the world are imploied for judgment, and all usurpers of power are under a Master, that is, higher then the highest, who make's use of them for the welfare of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; for although wee count not punishments our wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, yet certainly in God's hand they are for the good of his people, and they execute the wrath which God hath appointed against evil doers; and this wrath they execute by virtue of their office. For God appoint's them to the office, that they should take vengeance of evil doers, as <hi>Jehu</hi> was appointed against the hous of <hi>Ahab,</hi> in an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie cours.</p>
               <p>The last Argument alleged to prove, that no usurpers can bee meant by higher powers in <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. is taken from a supposed inconvenient consequence, which is, that if Levellers, Papists, or Malignants should get the power, and becom the supreme Rulers, wee should bee obliged to obeie them as the powers that are of God; whereunto I can saie no more but this; that it would indeed bee a sad case, if God should dispose of the Supremacie of power in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to such hands; but if hee should for a judgment over this state bee pleased so to do, I know none other rule for pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate men to behave themselvs by, but this which the Apostle doth prescribe; for if the Turk were my supreme Magistrate, and my lot did fall to bee under his civil Government, I would think my self bound, in things good and lawful, to submit unto him; the Reformed Churches in <hi>France</hi> are under a Papist Magistrate: yet they refuse not to submit in things good and lawful; If God give the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to the basest of men, and set mee under him, I must not saie, becaus hee is base, that therefore his power is not of God.</p>
               <p>Thus I have after a long delaie found som time, to offer your friends these thoughts for their satisfaction, the three first scruples I had answered above a moneth ago; the last which relates to <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. I intended to have answered by a full, and demonstrative Analysis of that whole context, which I had begun to make, but beeing severally inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted with som other occasions, I did yesterdaie alter my
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:58502:35"/> resolution, and have added to that, which was don so long ago; what you finde here, in answer to the fourth scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: the Lord direct us in all truth, and teach us to discern the things that are most excellent; I rest, and desire you to remember mee to your friends, as beeing</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your affectionate and faithful<lb/> Servant in Christ.</hi>
                     <lb/> JOHN DVRIE.</signed>
                  <lb/>
                  <dateline>S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
                     <hi>James's</hi>
                     <lb/>
                     <date>17. <hi>Julie</hi> 1650.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="letter">
               <head>The fourth Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Reverend Sir!</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Received yours of the <hi>17<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
                  </hi> of Julie, for which I must acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg my self obliged unto you, that you are pleased still to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue your labor of love, and care to give satisfaction to such, as desire it in a loving waie. The end of my answer at this time is to let you know that your Letter and Books came safely to my hands, and to return you manie thanks for both of them, which I have already communicated to som friends, and shall do to others. I will not seek to create you anie more trouble, by raising up anie new scruples, about those things you delivered in your letter, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly briefly acquaint you with their success, with som that I acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with them: Som think, that if what you hold forth about that place, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. will hold firm, it will bee a sufficient ground of satisfaction, for yielding obedience to the present powers. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth the engaging to do it much trouble them; if they should oblige themselvs to do it onely in a passive, not in an active waie: but they conciev, that by taking the engagement to bee faithful to the present government, they binde themselvs, not onely to bee subject to them in all lawful things; but to oppose, and resist anie other, to whom (as they in their conscience think) the right of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doth truly belong, when ever it shall bee claimed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Others that are truly godlie, think, that what you
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:58502:36"/> speak about the rule of beeing guided by the major part (that it is not alway the best and safest waie) holds true <hi>in rebus mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralibus,</hi> but not <hi>in rebus politicis,</hi> els the foundation of all go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment will bee overthrown; if in such things as are to bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined by Votes of divers persons, the major part may not carrie it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> They think, that what you saie in answer to the second scruple about judging (namely, that all particular men may take notice by the judgment of discretion, of the proceedings of their superiors, to swaie their resolutions to a rational concurrence, or non-concurrence, in things required of them in their places; these beeing your words make's much for them, for in the judgment of discretion, they conceiv, that the setting up of themselvs to bee the supreme, and sole higher powers of the Nation, and excluding others (to whom a right therein did properly belong, aswel as to themselvs) without the consent of the Kingdom, is not agreeable to the right rule, and therefore they dare not concur with them in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or approving of it, (as they shall do, if they take the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) other doubts might bee mentioned, but I will not bee tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; I finde that the Treatise of the <hi>Lancashier</hi>-Ministers about the Engagement, seem's to bee of great weight and strength with manie good men, if a cleer answer could bee given, to what there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is most substantial, it would give great satisfaction. I do most freely and feelingly assent to what you saie, and acknowledg that it is God's peculiar work, to make the wilderness of our spiritual estate a pool of waters, and to turn the drie land into waterie springs: to him therefore I desire to look, humbly imploring him, (who is <hi>the Father of lights</hi>) so to inform our judgments, that wee may bee able to see, and discern the things that differ, and to compose our affections, that wee may both entertein everie truth in love, and embrace one another in love, not giving waie to anie groundless prejudice, which may bee an hindrance of either of these. And go on still (good sir!) to bee the unchangeable, constant, and single-hearted peace-maker, not suffering your self to bee discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged by anie misapprehensions, that som (though good men) may have of you, for hee that seeth the heart, and tryeth the reins, will in due time recompe<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s what ever is don in truth of heart, for preserving of the <hi>unitie of the spirit in the bond of peace.</hi>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:58502:36"/> Inparticular, bee not wearie (as occasion serv's) in seeking to allaie the heat of indignation, that is stirred up in som in high place, against those that dare not venture upon the Engagement, (though forbearing upon grounds truly conscientious.) Our good God give unto all that fear him, that they may once com, to bee of one heart, and one waie, and all agree in that waie, which is most agreeable to his will and word.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your most affectionate, and<lb/> most obliged Brother, and<lb/> Servant in love.</signed>
                  <lb/>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>this</hi> 16<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of August<lb/> 1650.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="answer">
               <head>The Answer to the fourth Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Reverend Sir!</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOur's of the sixteenth of <hi>August</hi> was delivered unto mee the three and twentieth thereof; after which daie, I had occasion to go into the Countrie, which took mee off from these thoughts, almost ever since; but now I am returned unto them, to let you know, that the expressions of love in your Letter, and the encouragements which you give mee, to proceed in the waie wherein I am, are no small refreshments unto my spirit, and a support against the obloquies and reproaches, which I meet withal in the mouths of others: whose bissaed affections will not suffer them to look upon mee without prejudice: so that they cannot discern, in anie waie that simplicitie, by which I endeavor; as to offer my self to all men, so to approve my conscience before God. But som comfort I have, that this is no new thing unto mee; for all along, my lot hath been more or less, to bee misunderstood by all, and thus to bee look't upon a squint by one partie or another: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caus,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:58502:37"/> although I could not but approve alwaies in som things, one partie more then another, and consequently, for the main I did own them, as those amongst whom I was to bee reckoned; yet I never did own them as a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or in their partiships: but set my minde to cure them of the distempers, which proceed from the spirit of envie and jealousie, which dwel's in our flesh. Therefore so far as I understood my freedom in the spirit, I never was, nor ever shall bee (I hope) restrained from making use of all parties, and owning them in that which is good and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonant to the truth of Christianitie.</p>
               <p>I thank you for the account you are pleased to give mee of the success, which the papers I sent you have had with som; one of the chief aims which I have in this business (next unto the discoverie of Truth, to unite our spirits therein, and give satisfaction to those who are scrupled) is to engage the affections of godlie men, upon the thoughts of mutual forbearance, and compliance by shewing, that as there is no caus of fundamental division, between those that differ in judgment, about the present civil transactions; so there ought not to bee anie such di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of affections, as to produce anie unwillingness of beeing reconciled to each other; or of beeing reunited in the prosecution of their main design, which is a Gospel-Reformation of this Nation: to oblige therefore holie men to entertein the thoughts, which may lead them to this aim, is one of the causes, which make's mee so willing to bee larger upon this subject, then other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise I would bee; for what is it to mee, whether I stand under the government of one man, or of manie; if I can either waie fulfil my race with joie, and serv my Generation in the advancement of the Kingdom of the Lord Jesus? whatever Government then God doth set over mee, I look upon it, and upon my dutie in it, with a reference, and subordination unto this aim; nor is it at all lawful for mee, by anie humane Engagement whatsoë<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, to abridg my self of this libertie, or to forestal my self in this resolution: so that I should bee obliged to scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:58502:37"/> the performance of anie Christian duties for publick edification, more in a Common-wealth, then in a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie, or <hi>vice versâ:</hi> or that I may not (when God so cast's the ballance of humane affairs) determine it to bee my right, to live aswel under the one Government, as under the other, walking in Peace and Truth towards all men inoffensively. In effect by the scanning of matters relating to this subject, I finde that I am fallen upon a branch of the studie of Peace, which heretofore, in the pursuit thereof I never did reflect upon so directly: for in former times my direct aim was to minde onely the Rules of religious Peace and unitie amongst the professors of the Gospel, in reference to Christianitie; but now I have been carried on to minde also the Rules, by which a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian is obliged to behave himself peaceably, in civil and outward relations; which is, and will bee a necessarie point of knowledg, as wee are in the flesh, and as long as <hi>Babylon</hi> is not fallen, and the <hi>New Jerusalem,</hi> the mother of us all, is not com down from above. I have therefore caus to thank God, that as I have not been led forth by anie worldlie end, in medling with this Subject; So I have learned thereby, somwhat more of the waies of Peace, then ever I knew before. And that I may benefit my self by the occasion which you offer unto mee in your last; although you oblige mee not to tell you my sens, of that which your friends conceiv of my last answers to their doubts, yet I shall briefly take into consideration, the thoughts which you have expressed of theirs, concerning som pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sages of my discours.</p>
               <p>The first is concerning active obedience, to bee yielded unto the present powers, which upon the ground of <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. I think may cleerly bee made out; <hi>but they conceiv</hi> (as you saie) <hi>that by taking the Engagement to bee faithful to the present Government, they binde themselvs not onely to bee subject unto them in all lawful things; but to oppose, and resist anie other, to whom (as they in their conscience think) the right of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doth truly belong; when ever it shall bee obteined.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I conceiv, that the sens of the Engagement cannot ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:58502:38"/> otherwise bee understood; then as the autors thereof in the Act, by which it is imposed upon all, do explain their meaning; and conscionably it may, and ought to bee understood none otherwise, then as it conteineth a cleer dutie prescribed in the word of God: nor can anie man, as a Christian, intend to bee obliged otherwise unto it, then as it is in it self, and so far as it is to him a dutie; nor ought anie man (that will not injure his Superiors in his thoughts) that it is imposed by them in anie other sens, then as it is such a dutie; if godlie men there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore should minde in simplicitie themselvs, and their own duties, what need they set stumbling blocks in their own waie, by conjectural interpretations of things; which they conceiv contrarie to dutie in others? Is not this a subtil corruption of nature to bee so inclined; and a weakness of spirit to do so? and if wee represent things so to our selvs, that wee becom thereby disaffected to our own du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, becaus wee are willing to conceiv that somthing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dutiful in others, may follow thereupon; do wee not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv our selvs with the possibilitie of another's failing, in time to com, to make it a pretence to cover our own pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent failing? for if it bee our present dutie, to becom faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the powers that are over us, by doing things good and lawful under them; to what purpose is it to forestal our thoughts with a thing, which wee cannot saie is; or which wee know not, whether it ever shall bee; <hi>viz.</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our Superiors will oppose anie, to whom the right of Government doth truly belong? They that are in the full possession of power, are under God, at this time, our onely Superiors and Governors: nor is it lawful for mee at present to have anie relation, and therefore I ought not to have anie respect unto others; for it is cleerly my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, in my sphere, to observ with a single heart the relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, under which by God's appointment I stand at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent; nor am I to meddle with anie thing els, as a matter of conscience, but with the observation of the Rule, <hi>Let all souls bee subject to the superior powers, and the powers that are, are ordained of God,</hi> Rom. 13. If then I take upon mee,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:58502:38"/> to make it a matter of conscience to think, that the right of government in chief, doth truly belong to others, then to these that are in place; do not I depose them in my heart, and make my self the judg of their supremacie? and if I suppose that they do oppose, or will oppose those, to whom I have adjudged the supreme Right; do not I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the qualitie of a Subject, and of a private man, by taking upon mee, to determine the highest controversie in our humane affairs, which is, to whom the Right of Government in this state doth belong; and how I should bee able, to warrant in my self (who am in no place) and to my conscience before God, this usurpation of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature over my Superiors, (who are undeniably in the full possession of all places of Judicature) while's I accuse them of another kinde of usurpation, I am not able to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine: for there is no Rule, either of God or man, that make's them subject to my tribunal. I would therefore intreat your friends in the fear of God, to examine the ground, and consider conscionably by what Rule, they dare take upon them to engage their conscience thus, to think, that the right of Government doth truly belong to anie other, then to the present Parlament, which is pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessed therewith. This presupposal of their's, determin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the right to another, not onely beg's the Question in debate; but contein's a high charge against all the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamentarie proceedings hitherto, prosecuted against the King's attempts, to rule without Law; It bewraie's there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not onely a great deal of presumption, but much un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advisedness of Conscience, to cast themselvs thereby into a snare of disobedienee; and the State wherein they live, into all unsettlement and confusion. For private men, if they should bee made judges of publick quarrels: and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged in conscience, to yield no active obedience towards the maintenance of the settlement, which is in beeing under their Superior powers, except the ground of the quarrel bee referred to them to determine, it is not possible that there could bee anie settlement in a State at all; therefore private men are not to answer for the grounds of the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:58502:39"/> quarrels, which may bee between their own supreme pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and others that pretend to the same Dignitie; but all that they are obliged unto, is, by lawful means in their places, to defend and maintein in peace, the settlement which is in beeing, and to act with their Rulers to that effect.</p>
               <p>The second is, touching the Rule of beeing guided by the major part; where it is granted, that <hi>in rebus morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus my rule held true, but not in rebus Politicis; els</hi> (saie they) <hi>the foundation of all Government will bee overthrown, if in things to bee determined by Votes of divers persons, the Major part may not carrie it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I said in matters of extraordinarie concernment, a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor part is not to bee bound by the Votes of a Major part; hereunto your friends seem to agree so far, as matters are Moral, but not as they are Political; what they mean properly by Political, I do not well know; but I meant matters of Government, which relate unto the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal constitution of safetie and libertie; which are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies either materially, or formally complicated with Moral Duties, or elsimmediately depending upon the same; but in lesser matters, which relate not unto the grounds of libertie and safetie, which perhaps your friends call <hi>Politica,</hi> I consent with them, that the Major part should carrie it; and that all rational men should for peace sake, yield in things not worth a great contest: as in matters of meer order, what is to bee don, or taken into conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration first, or last: in matters of circumstance, relating to forms of actions, to times and places, and to the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of proceeding, which doth not alter the substance of things morally good: and in particular municipal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitutions, which have no influence upon the whole state of a Common-wealth; in all such things the Major part should binde the Minor to a concurrence, lest all the grounds of Societie bee dissolved; but when the business relate's unto the main end, and chief grounds of publick safetie and freedom, then although the thing to bee setled may bee called Political, in respect of the State for which
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:58502:39"/> it is desired; yet it will alwaies bee found in respect of the obligation, which thereby will bee brought upon the cours of particular men's lives, a matter of moralitie.</p>
               <p>The third thing which you mention, is their sens of my Answer to the second scruple, concerning the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of discretion, how far, and to what end, private men may make use of it; here I finde in them, either a mistake of the Notion, which I have of the judgment of discretion, or els a misapplication thereof, in respect of the limits, how far it is to bee extended, or of the end and use for which it is allowed. To cleer their thoughts, I shall desire them to take notice, that, by the judgment of discretion, I mean a rational, free, and disingaged surveying of things, which offer themselves to our consideration, about mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters whereof wee may lawfully make enquirie; with an eie of indifferencie to make som discoveries, but may not make anie absolute and final determination thereof; so as to oblige our Conscience to follow the result of our disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries: for wee may lawfully enquire further then wee may define; and it may bee profitable and advantagious for us, as to the manner of doing our duties, to make discoveries of the waies of those, towards whom in those Duties wee do relate; and yet not necessarie for us, as to the performance of the main of the Dutie on our part, to define anie thing by those discoveries concerning them. For herein the judgment of discretion, and the definitive judgment of Conscience differ in my Notion; that the one is necessarie in reference to our selvs, and is to bee absolute about matters, relating properly to our own sphere of activitie, wherein there is a cleer Rule for everie man to determine, what is his Dutie: but the other is free and voluntarie in reference to others, and is to bee alwaies conditional, about matters relating properly to the sphere of other men's activitie; wherein, although the general rule of dutie may bee known, yet the particular circumstances of fact beeing unknown, no setled judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can bee made of the lawfulness, or unlawfulness of their proceedings; and therefore no consequences may bee
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:58502:40"/> drawn from the discoveries made, concerning other men's actions, whereof wee cannot bee judges, to define matters of dutie concerning our selvs: becaus nothing of dutie, relating to our selvs in our places, can bee suspended upon the doubtful circumstances of other men's actings in their places.</p>
               <p>From all which you may perceiv, what bounds I set to the judgment of discretion, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>First,</hi> that it must rise from our rational facultie, and not from our Conscience, that is, the motive which should put us upon the exercising of this judgment, must not bee a tie of Conscience to resolv a scruple; but a rational con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of that, which may bee advantagious to our understanding; by the discoverie of those properties of things, which occur to us in our waie, which will inable us to make good use thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> that the object of the judgment of Discretion must bee things without, and not things within; for things within, if they bee our own, wee are bound to judg these definitively; but if they bee the secrets of other men, wee must leav them to the judgment of him, that will reveal the hidden things of darkness: as for things without, which others do act; wee are to look upon them discreetly, and with a limitation, upon certain conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; leaving the definitive sentence thereof to the <hi>judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the great daie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> that the judgment of discretion is onely to bee entended to the circumstantials of matters, to make a true discoverie thereof; and not to the substantials, to prie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond our line, into the secrets and main concernments of other men, as busie bodies in other men's matters.</p>
               <p>As for the end and use, for which the judgment of discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is to bee allowed, I conceiv thus.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is to bee exercised to inable us, to discern proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, what the nature and propertie of things are, which from without are incident to us in our waie, as offered from others: that wee may difference that which is useful, from that which is useless; lest wee mistake the one for
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:58502:40"/> the other, in that application, which wee shall have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion to make thereunto.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That it is to bee exercised, to keep our spirit in the use of our Libertie; so, as neither to fall under the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of an implicite credulitie, to believ everie thing that is told us; nor to take too much upon us, as magisterial Judges, or controlers of men, or things not within our line; but discreetly to ballance our thoughts, between a slavish belief, and a busie prying into, and censoriousness of other men's affairs.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That the result of it must not bee to regulate the main of our cours, thereby either in our own place, or to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards others; but onely to help us in the manner of proceeding, to do things more completely, and satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factorie to our own reason, and the edification of others; it must not therefore giue us the rule of that, which is, or is not to bee don in our places; but it may discover unto us, that which may tend to the <hi>bene</hi> or <hi>meliùs esse,</hi> thereof in reference to others.</p>
               <p>These Notions I laie open to your friends, that they may perceiv their mistake in the consequence, which they infer upon my words, whereby they confound the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of discretion, with that which is definitive; and misapplie the former to the object of the later: for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caus I saie, that <hi>particular men may by the judgment of discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, take notice of the actions of their Superiors, to swaie their resolutions to a rational concurrence, or non-concurrence in things required of them in their places;</hi> they conclude (as they conceiv) by the judgment of discretion, that, <hi>what the present powers have don, in setling themselvs in the Supremacie, is not agreeable to the rule of righteousness: wherefore</hi> (saie they) <hi>they dare not concur in doing, or approving of it, as they shall do, if they take the Engagement.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this conclusion, I saie it follow's not upon my asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but that they mistake the nature, and the use of the judgment of discretion; and misapplie it to make up an absolute definition of a thing, which is not within the line of their Judicature; for they determine upon the whole
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:58502:41"/> matter, that the superioritie of their Rulers is unjust; whereas discretion and conscience, both should teach them not to determine anie thing of so high a nature; onely they might modestly take leav to make a rational search into the circumstances, and a discoverie of probabilities alleged <hi>in utramque partem, pro &amp; contrà;</hi> Nor should that discoverie, how probable soëver it may seem on either side, becom a ground to bottom the main of their dutie upon; but it should onely serv to swaie their resolutions, to a rational concurrence, or non-concurrence, in things required of them in their places. By things required of them in their places, I mean particular matters, which are to bee don in order to their main and known dutie, which is to bee subject to superior powers, in all good things, and by a rational concurrence, or non-concurrence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, I mean an intelligent discerning of our waie, in respect of the manner, how to act, or not to act with others there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, for the publick good, so as may bee most advantagious, and acceptable to these, towards whom, and with whom the action is to bee intended; therefore when they reflect upon the present powers, in reference to their Supremacie; so as to saie, that in their judgment of discretion, they finde, that what the powers have don for their settlement, is not agreeable to righteousness; they judg not discreet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but rashly; becaus they indiscreetly applie their thoughts to an object, which is beyond the line, and against the use of the judgment of discretion; and furthermore, upon this their indiscreet judgment of that, whereof they they are not made judges; they infer as indiscreet a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion; for they saie, therefore they dare non-concur in approving of the proceedings, by which their Superiors are com to bee setled in the Supremacie: as they think they shall do, if they take the Engagement: here they having misapplied their judgment to a wrong object, they act not discreetly, but definitively about it: for they saie, they dare not concur in approving of what their Superiors have don; but who doth require this approbation at the hand of their Conscience? For that onely should teach them
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:58502:41"/> what to dare, or not to dare; and it would bee well, if such as dare not concur in approving, should also not dare to concur, in disapproving what they have don: but when they have defined the matter to bee unrighteous, contrarie to the law of discretion; and then saie, that therefore they dare not concur to approve; they declare sufficiently that they dare concur to the contrarie, <hi>viz.</hi> to disapprove, which is to make themselvs the supreme Judges of Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie; but neither the one, nor the other is to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired at their hands, or imposed upon their Conscience; for their dutie is discreetly to leav that unto God, and to time to manifest, and in the mean time to do sincerely their dutie. But now, becaus they are out of the waie of dutie in all this, and prepossessed with an indiscreet judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; therefore they also misinterpret the taking of the Engagement, as if it should oblige their consciences to make a definition of things past, by waie of approbation; whereas, by the verie Act by which it is enjoined, it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that the purpose of taking it, is onely to look from the present state of affairs, foreward, and not backward,. to secure the publick Peace and safetie in time to com, by the present settlement, and not to oblige anie to trouble himself with things past: therefore herein also is no right of the judgment, either of discretion or of definition, for the conscionable and definitive judgment should have taught them, to look upon the sens of the Engagement, onely as it is a cleer dutie, so far as it is expressed in the words, declaring manifestly the purpose thereof, and not otherwise; but they having engaged their thoughts by prejudice, in another waie of Judicature, have not at all regarded this Rule, but made a definition quite contrarie thereunto, to take themselvs off from due respect and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to their Superiors, upon a pretence of their failing in the highest point of their dutie, which neither discreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor conscience will ever allow them to determine.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:58502:42"/>
            <head>The Appendix concerning the <hi>Cheshier</hi> and <hi>Lancashier-</hi>Minister's Plea for <hi>Non-Subscribers.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THese are my thoughts of the doubts which you men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to bee in the thoughts of your friends: one thing as an <hi>Appendix</hi> you add more, which as an <hi>appendix</hi> to all these foregoing discourses between you and mee, I shall further also consider: and therewith conclude all fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conferences on this Subject, except you shall desire the continuance thereof.</p>
            <p>Your words are these. <hi>I finde</hi> (saie you) that <hi>the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise of the Lancashier-Ministers seem's to bee of great weight and strength, with manie good men: If a cleer Answer could bee given, to what therein is most substantial, it would give great satisfaction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly I do confess, that that Treatise hath a seeming strength in it; and I believ that it doth take much with manie good men, that are oft-times but weakly principled in these matters; but I must confess, that to mee, that Treatise hath no weight nor strength at all; and becaus you laie it before mee, as a means to give great satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if there were a cleer Answer given to that, which therein is most substantial, I shall with as much brevitie as I can, shew you wherein I finde it substantially weak.</p>
            <p>First then, I shall offer to your consideration, whether at all, by all which they have said, anie of these grounds bee shaken, which I have insisted upon all along, to shew the conscionableness of taking the Engagement; to my understanding (I profess) I finde not that they have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly touched, or medled with anie of my grounds to anie purpose at all; for which caus, as I have no Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at all upon my spirit, to deal with their plea: so I think it neither needful, nor discretion in mee, to take the task of other men upon mee, who are better able to
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:58502:42"/> maintein their own positions then I am: therefore I shall saie nothing to the whole <hi>Appendix</hi> of their Treatise, which contein's the Answers which they give to the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which other defenders of the Engagement have brought for it; and the Replies which they make to the solutions of the doubts, which are alleged against it: wherein little or nothing is touched of that, which is my plea for it.</p>
            <p>But secondly, if I were to deal upon som other account, with these Non-subscribers about their Plea, either in cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to themselvs, to set them right; or in compassion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards others, to undeceiv such as think their reasons weightie, I would saie nothing to their preliminarie dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses, from page the first till the tenth, for as I would have all men bee towards my self; so I would bee towards them in my thoughts; and consequently, I do charitably believ of them, that they have truly delivered not onely the <hi>se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> of their thoughts, concerning their own case and condition, in reference to the present and former estate of affairs; but also the motives which have consciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly induced them to publish the reasons of their dissatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction at the taking of the Engagement; nor would I set my self to observ narrowly the Method of their proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; but I would endevor in simplicitie and truth, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine and remove the grounds of their dissatisfaction, that their desires so far as they are truly christian, and equita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble might bee fulfilled: and with these preliminarie dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions of minde, on my part, I would first com to state the Question between mee and them, to know how inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent upon the whole matter, their plea for non-subscrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing might bee found: and then in the second place, I would propose the Principles, and the manner of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, by which wee might com to the decision, and determination of that Question. These things would bee requisite to handle the matter throughly with them: but to let you, or anie equitable reader understand, where the invaliditie of the substance of their plea doth lie, as to my conception; I shall not need to proceed by so manie
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:58502:43"/> degrees; for one that is not prepossessed, as the Pleaders may bee, it will suffice to shew, what the full strength of their whole plea is, as they propose it; and then where that strength doth fail them to make out their main pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose.</p>
            <p>Their main purpose is to shew, that to subscribe the Engagement, is a thing inconsistent with a good Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and therefore ought not to bee pressed upon them.</p>
            <p>To make this appear, they do two things; First, they construe the Engagement, and declare the sens, wherein they think it is to bee taken. Secondly, they allege the reasons, for which they cannot take and subscribe it, in that sens and construction: Now if it bee made evident, either that they wholly misconstrue the Engagement, and therefore ought not to take it in that sens, wherein they declare they understand it; or that supposing their sens in som respect to bee tolerable; yet that the main grounds of the Reasons which they rais upon that sens, will not reach to the proof of their conclusion; then I suppose, it will cleerly follow, that their whole discours is of no soliditie: not onely, becaus they mistake the whole case of Conscience in reference to the Engagement; and so bring in all their reasons upon a meer mistake; but also, becaus the grounds of their reasons are not sound to evince their purpose, although the case were not mistated. Now to mee, both these waies the Treatise is unsatisfactorie; for I think it may bee made out very fully; that they not onely misunderstand the Engagement; but that their reasons prove not what they intend, for so far as they misunderstand it not.</p>
            <p>First, I shall shew you where to mee their mistake lie's, in the sens of the Engagement; and then where their main Reasons are not sound to oblige consciences. Concerning the meaning of the Engagement, they first allege the words; and then complain of the generalitie and ambigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itie thereof; and lastly, deliver the sens, wherein they conceiv it ought to bee taken, by the opening of three things.</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:58502:43"/>
               <item>1. The Object
<list>
                     <item>of the Engagement.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2. The Matter</item>
               <item>3. The Form</item>
            </list>
            <p>By the object they understand a positive, and particular form of Government, erected in the Land, and invested in certain persons, expressed in these words. <hi>The Common-wealth of England, as it is now established without a King and Hous of Lords.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the matter in the words, <hi>I will bee true and faithful,</hi> they understand not a meer negative and passive cessation, and succumbencie; but a positive devotedness to obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and active diligence in doing things commanded; and a mainteining of the Government in beeing, against all competitors, especially against the excluded King, and Hous of Lords; and aversion from promoting anie other government while's this Engagement is in force.</p>
            <p>By the Form of the Engagement, in the words, <hi>I do declare and promise that I will;</hi> they understand an obligation for time to come, indeterminately and without limitation; so that it is onely in the will of the engaged to, to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the length of the duration of the Engagement.</p>
            <p>That which they saie, concerning the matter and form of the Engagement, they stand not much upon; nor shall I think amiss of it, becaus in som respect, all may bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; but the corner-stone of their future building, is that which they saie concerning the object, or the partie engaged to; which I do think, is a very gross mistake, as they have stated it. The words of the Engagement ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressing the object, are well alleged, to bee <hi>the Common-wealth of England as it is now established, without a King and Hous of Lords;</hi> but the sens which they make of this Common-wealth, as thus established, that nothing els should bee meant by it, but a <hi>positive and particular form of Government lately erected, and invested in certain persons,</hi> is a cleer mistake of the whole foundation of their Plea, against the taking of the Engagement, and maketh all that is built thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to bee ruinous: and although they seem to allege som colorable reasons, why these words of the Engagement
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:58502:44"/> are to bee taken in this sens; yet if the grounds which they pretend to have, for that construction of the words of the Engagement bee rightly weighed, they will appear exceeding weak: and evidently contrarie to the minde of the autors of the Engagement, and their words in the express Declarations, directly relating to this matter, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the rational construction of the words of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, look't upon barely in themselvs: and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to the Rules of Christian equitie, and ingenuitie, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servable by good subjects in a business of this nature.</p>
            <p>First, by the Margin of their Plea, they intend to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor their interpretation from the words of an Act, for a daie of humiliation, <hi>April.</hi> 19. 1649. and out of som other Acts indefinitely vouched; which intimate onely that, <hi>there is a government now setled in the waie of a Common-wealth, or free-state:</hi> I shall grant willingly, that these words are truly vouched; but from them I denie, that it can bee rightly inferred, that therefore the sole and main object of the Engagement is nothing els but the Government, as it is erected, and invested in certain persons; for the settlement <hi>of a Government in the waie of a Common-wealth</hi> is a thing mainly distinct from that, which is meant properly by a Common-wealth; for such a settlement doth presuppose, that there is a Common-wealth in beeing: for how can a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment bee setled in a Nation after the waie of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, except you presuppose that Nation to have the beeing of a Common-wealth? that is, to bee a State free from servitude, to the dominion of one man's will, to bee a Common-wealth, therefore is somwhat antecedent, to the having of a Government setled in the waie of a Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>But secondly, to put it out of all doubt, that this is the true meaning of the autors of the Engagement; I shall refer you, not to som Declarations of theirs, which speak collaterally, and by the by of this matter; as these plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders do, to lead themselvs and others into a mistake; but to the Declarations, wherein the autors of the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment speak to this matter of set purpose, which the <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cashier</hi>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:58502:44"/> Ministers ought to have heeded; becaus, <hi>Ignorantia legis neminem excusat.</hi> There is then an Act, <hi>Die Sabbathi</hi> 19. <hi>Maie,</hi> 1640. whereof the title is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Act declaring, and constituting the people of</hi> England, <hi>to bee a Common-wealth and Free State;</hi> and the words thereof are these in the following Paragraphs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bee it declared and enacted by this present Parlament, and the Autoritie of the same, that the people of England, and of all the Dominions and territories thereunto belonging, are and shall bee, and are hereby constituted, made, and established, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed to bee a Common-wealth and free State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the first part of the Act, by which wee see cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as also by the title, that they mean properly, by the Common-wealth of <hi>England</hi> the People collectively taken in their National relation.</p>
            <p>The second part of the Act followeth in these words. <hi>And shall from henceforth bee governed as a</hi> Common-wealth, <hi>and</hi> free-State, <hi>by the supreme Autoritie of this Nation, the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentatives of the People in Parlament, and by such as they shall appoint, and constitute, as Officers and Ministers under them, for the good of the people; and that without anie King and Hous of Lords.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the whole Act, by which it is as cleer as the Sun at noon daie, that they take a Common-wealth original<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and properly to bee antecedent to the Government established in it; and therefore that their meaning is, that the object of our fealtie should bee directly, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly the Common-wealth in this sens; and the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment reductively, as it is setled in a Common-wealth-waie, which they define to bee in the supreme and subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate Officers; the supreme to bee <hi>Representatives of the People in Parlament,</hi> and the subordinate to bee such, as <hi>they shall appoint and constitute under them, &amp;c.</hi> whence to my understanding it followeth undeniably, as also from the title, by which the Parlament doth style it self, <hi>viz. the Parlament of the Common-wealth of England;</hi> that the direct, and principal object of Truth, and faithfulness set before us in the Engagement, is the beeing of a Common-wealth,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:58502:45"/> as in the Act it is explained and established, and that the collateral object of Truth and faithfulness depending here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon and offered to us in the Engagement as subordinate thereunto, is the manner of the establishment now in bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, without a King and Hous of Lords; which is the Government in a Common-wealth-waie by Representatives in Parlament, and Officers appointed by them: and as for their expression of the matter; viz. That it is <hi>a Government as it is now erected and invested in certain persons,</hi> it tend's evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently to corrupt the Reader's minde with a jealousie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the persons in place, as if they would exalt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selvs by the Engagement to bee alone respected as the whole Common-wealth; which I am persuaded is far from their thought.</p>
            <p>From all which appeareth, that they complain with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out caus a of <hi>Protean</hi> ambiguitie, and too great a Generali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the words of the Engagement: General and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguous words are not all one thing: True Generals have as proper a sens in their Comprehensiveness, as particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars have in their Circumscription. But now (becaus men love to misconstrue) when to prevent mistakes, the words are explained in proper significant terms, in what sens they are to bee taken (as by the aforesaid Act is don<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) then to mis-interpret them odiously against the sens of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, is not well excusable in the Interpreters. As for An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguous words, they are properly such as may bear a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent sens of things no waie agreeing in nature, nor any where explained, nor explainable by any rational constru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction made of them by other words whereunto they are joined; which also cannot bee said of the words of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, if onely lookt upon by themselvs, in reference to the proposed scope of those that do impose the same. For no intelligent man, looking impartially upon these words, with a reference to the declared aim of those that impose the same can make rationally anie other constru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction thereof then this; That the object of his Truth and Faithfulness must bee first immediately and directly the Common-wealth of <hi>England;</hi> and then secondarily by waie
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:58502:45"/> of Reduction, and in order thereunto, the Establishment of this Common-wealth as now it stand's by the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Parlament, without a King and Hous of Lords; for all intelligent men, if they will bethink themselvs, may know, that the word <hi>Common-wealth</hi> is taken somtimes for the Collective, somtimes for the Representative Bodie of a people; and that without all ambiguitie; becaus these two Bodies are not in the nature of Humane societie of different kindes; but beeing from one Principle, and to one end, they are alwaies to bee understood joint in their existence, and by their natural properties complicated together; and yet they may bee conceived, and are somtimes offred to our thoughts as distinct in their order and notions: therefore when in the same speech both the notions are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinctly intimated and offered to our apprehehension, and that in their due subordination, it is very irrational for anie man to reject that which is the first and Principal, and take hold onely of the second and subordinate. Now in the words of the Engagement both these Notions are offered as distinct, and in their natural order expressed; for the first and principal Notion; which is the collective Common-wealth, is made the immediate and direct object of our promise as it is distinguished from the other by the denomination of England, which signifie's the bodie of the Nation, as if it were said, <hi>I shall bee true and faithful to the People of this Land in their free state and national rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to each other, for common welfare.</hi> And then the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and subordinate Notion which is the Representative Common-wealth is made the reductive and mediate object of the Engagement; as it is distinguished from the former by the reduplicative expressions, <hi>As it is now established:</hi> and the explanatorie termes relating to this establishment, <hi>without a King or Hous of Lords.</hi> now to make the reduplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive matter of the Engagement to bee the sole object of the promise, when the direct matter is in express termes before mentioned, and to make the representative Common-wealth, the sole thing meant, when the collective or repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented Common-wealth is not onlie presupposed in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:58502:46"/> of the thing; but in express words first mentioned, is to mee very irrational and far from ingenuitie, although there were none other exposition of the words else where exstant: but now when both the words in their frame and dispositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on lie so fair, and there is so clear an expression of them els<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where; then to complain of so much ambiguitie, and upon that complaint to arrest the sens so far; bewraie's a great deal of partialitie and forestalement in the mindes of those that so take it up.</p>
            <p>Besides al this, another consideration doth offer it self which may discover the aim of the autors of the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and their sens in imposing it, and will make anie im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partialman, who can rationally construe men's actions as wel as their words, perceiv, that the main object of the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment cannot bee meant the sole government as invested in certain persons; becaus the persons, who are said to bee the object of the Engagement, do all of them take the same Engagement themselvs, and in the same sens wherein it is offered to others to bee taken: now to say that they in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it make themselvs the sole object of their Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and do understand by the word <hi>Common-wealth of England</hi> nothing els but themselves, is to mee so absurd, that I cannot imagine it to be incident to men of ingenuitie; and so injurious to their publick professions (whereby they have declared so manie waies that their Engagements and undertakings are wholly for the People of the land colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively, as they are a Nation; to bee true and faithful to them and to their Libertie) that, for conscience sake, I dare not suspect them to mean otherwise then they profess. And if upon these grounds I am obliged rationally to beleiv that this is the main object of their taking the Engagement, I must also conclude that they intend others should take it in the same waie. And as for the establishment whereof they themselvs are a part being taken not individually but in their state-relation, it is no absurditie that in order to the main object, their state-constitution should bee a secondarie obiect whereunto each of them should bee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged: and in what sens they are engaged thereunto, it
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:58502:46"/> is their meaning that all who take the Engagement should bee analogically in like manner engaged. Now they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee otherwise engaged, to their own state-relation and constitution; but as they are members of the Nation, and so far as they understand that constitution to bee subordinable to the good of the Common-wealth in a collective sens: therefore no bodie els can or ought to bee otherwise en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged thereunto, but as they relate unto the Nation, and as the constitution of the government is in that subordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And I am very confident that none of them will saie, nor anie that understand themselvs will think oherwise. As for mine own part in all businesses of this Nature, which concern subjection and obedience unto Superior Powers; I conceiv the Rules of Christian Equitie and Ingenuitie ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige mee not to interpret either the actions or the words of my superiors suspitiously in the affection of State-jealousie; but to make the best Construction of them which they pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibly can in reason bear; the best use of them which I can according to my dutie intend: and answerable to this rule I have declared my sens of the Engagement, so far as I found in it a clear dutie; and my willingness to bee true and faithful to that dutie. And this is the rule by which I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv an ingenious Christian ought to interpret the purpose of the Engagement. Nor is it equitable in him to think that his Christian Rulers would desire anie thing more of him by it, then what this doth com to: therefore I trouble not my head with anie Political onstructions, or conjectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral events of my Superior's proceedings, to puzzle my self or others therewith; if I walk within mine own sphere of sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection by a clear rule, I shall bee inclined to wish and hope that others may do so also within their sphere of superio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie; but if they fail, I am not their Judg, I must leav them to God, and bee sorrie for that which seem's to bee their failing; and praie that if it bee a fault, God would rectifie it. Thus you see, how to mee, their main and fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal position, whereupon their whole plea is afterward grounded, is a meer mistake, and that a very gross one: for they having thus misconstrued the object of the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:58502:47"/> upon this mis-stated case they draw up their whole plea in two heads of arguments, whereof the first is taken from the questionableness of this object; the second from their obligation to their former Engagements. The plea taken from the questionableness of this object is from <hi>pag.</hi> 12 till 35 under two heads. The first is from the <hi>Thesis,</hi> and general position; That no man can warrantably oblige himself to bee true and faithful to a power or state gotten and held unjustly, whether to afford it a permissive suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferance, or an active support: This is handled from <hi>pag.</hi> 12 til 19. The second is from the <hi>Hypothesis</hi> or particular Position that this present power to bee engaged to, is both gotten and held unjustly: which they endeavor to make out in two respects; first in respect of the Government re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved or dispossessed, which is insisted upon from <hi>pag.</hi> 19. til 26. Secondly in respect of that which is erected in stead thereof from <hi>pag.</hi> 26 till 35.</p>
            <p>These are the heads of the first plea; the sum of all which com's to this; that seeing none ought to oblige him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self to bee true and faithful to a power which is unjustly gotten and held; <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 12.</note> becaus none ought to partake of, <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 13, 14.</note> or abet with, <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 15</note> and co-operate in, other men's sins; but all ought rather, and especially Ministers, to oppose sin in all; <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 16, 17, 18, 19.</note> therefore none ought to oblige himself to be true and faithful to this present power; becaus this present power is unlawfully gotten by the dispossessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and removing of the former Government <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 20, <hi>till</hi> 26.</note> without law and right to do so <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 26, 27, 28.</note>; and by the erection and investing of it self, <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 26, 27, 28.</note> which is a power not known what it is, <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 26, 27, 28.</note> nor where it is placed, <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 26, 27, 28.</note> nor whence it com's f and is short to <note place="margin">h <hi>Pag.</hi> 30.</note> anie ordinarie use, <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 29.</note> and manie waies injurious to the King, Prince, and Peers, and to their respective hereditarie dignities and powers, to the Hous of Lords, to the Hous of Commons, <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 31, 32.</note> to the People, and to the Laws of the Land <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 33, 34.</note>. Thus the first plea, supposing the object of the Engagement to bee nothing els but the present powers, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue's against them.</p>
            <p>Their second plea, relating to former Engagements hath
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:58502:47"/> two branches in like manner; the one is from their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingagement, as Subjects, from <hi>pag.</hi> 35 till 43; the other from their preingagement by sacred oaths from <hi>pag.</hi> 43 till 57: the sum of all which com's to this; That the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whereof the present powers are the sole object of Truth and faithfulnes; ought not to bee taken, becaus they are under a tie of subjection to powers Diametrically op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posite to these <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 35, 36.</note> which are still in beeing; and not at all abolished, <note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 37, 38.</note> neither by a judicial decree of the settled and supreme Autoritie, nor by anie forcible erection, <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 39, 40.</note> nor by God, <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 41.</note> nor by the original constitution of the people, <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 42.</note> nor by anie Laws or Statutes <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 43.</note>: and becaus they are under sacred oaths, <note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 44 <hi>till</hi> 51</note> which are diametrically opposite to the powers set up by the Engagement, and which continue still in force to oblige them as unrepealed and unrepealable <note n="s" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 51, <hi>till</hi> 57</note>. This is the whole strength of their plea: it run's all along upon this mistake, That the Engagement doth intend one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>to oblige us to Certain Persons, who style themselvs the Common-wealth, as it is now established without King and Lords,</hi> as they themselvs cleerly say <hi>pag.</hi> 29, and taking this as granted, (which I have shewed to be contrarie to the manifest declaration whereby the Common-wealth is constituted, contrarie to the Rational sens of the words of the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment considered by themselvs, and compared with that which the Autors thereof intend by their own taking of it; and contrarie to the equitie and Ingenuitie of Christian men requisite in business of this nature) they build a plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible, but unsound, plea against the Engagement, by contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the lawful standing of the present Government. But to overthrow their whole plea at one blow, by that Act which I have evidenced, to bee the true object of the Engagement; I shall argue thus. That Engagement which require's nothing els, but that everie one should bee true and faithful to the Freedom, and Common well-fare of the Nation; as these are now atteinable by the establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wherein it stand's, everie member of the Nation is bound to take; nor can anie preingagement whatsoëver lawfully hinder anie from taking the same. But this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:58502:48"/> Engagement require's nothing els but this: therefore all are bound to take it; and there can bee no preingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment lawful to hinder the taking thereof; as for them, they wrest the sens of the Engagement to pick a quarrel against the Autors thereof, that they may bring in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of fact, concerning the change of the Government odiously against them, and that they may take an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie to interpret the circumstances of their proceedings in reference to the change, as inconsistent with known Laws, and former engagements; but I finding that the Engagement in the obvious and rational sens, wherein it becom's everie private man, and good Christian to reflect upon it, doth contein a cleer Dutie, which I am bound to close with; I give my assent freely to it without anie more ado; and although I am not ignorant, that the Engagement it self doth presuppose a change befal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len to the State of the Nation; yet, becaus it doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly oblige mee to look upon the Common-wealth onely, as now setled; and in time to com, to perform a lawful dutie towards it, therefore I am not obliged to ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel into former matters, which were antecedent to the change, to examine what hath been don to bring it about, and whether it is com to pass warrantably, or unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantably: for I finde not that God doth binde the decisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that matter, to determine the lawfulness or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfulness thereof, upon the Conscience of anie private man, such as I am, nor will hee have mee to suspend a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which is necessarie <hi>in praesenti,</hi> upon the disquirie of such disputable matters; therefore when these pleaders ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige everie private man, to ravel into matters of fact past, and to intangle their Consciences into the Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the causes of the change, before they will suffer them to engage, to bee true and faithful to the Common-wealth as now it standeth, they take tacitely for granted, that which by no means is to bee yielded; and which I in my first considerations have cleerly denied, and proved not to bee warrantable, <hi>viz.</hi> that everie private man may conscionably take upon him, to bee a Judg of the right,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:58502:48"/> or wrong management of publick affairs; here then is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other great weakness of the plea; that before they either make it out, or attempt to shew it lawful for private men to becom Judges of the causes of publick changes, so as to make that Judicature a matter of Conscience to themselvs, they actually undertake upon a conscientious account that judicature, &amp; impose it upon the consciences of their unwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Readers, definitively to bee look't into; and in effect ground all the reasons of their plea upon this bottom, (which they have no right to determine) <hi>viz.</hi> that the change of Government hath not been lawfully brought about; and consequently, that the present powers have no right to their places; and consequently, that it is a sin against the Conscience of good subjects, and Christian Covenanters to promise (at the requiring of the present Powers) to bee true and faithful in time to com, to the Common-welfare of the people of the Land, as it is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teinable by the present constitution, which is without a King and Hous of Lords. Now although I should sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose (for argument's sake) their premises, that the change which hath befallen to the government of this Nation, was not lawfully brought about, as to the manner of proceeding therein; yet if I bee lawfully convicted, that it is beyond my sphere, to take upon mee the Judicature of that unlawfulness; and if it bee made probable unto mee by all the former proceedings of Parlament, that for the safetie of the Nation, there was a necessitie of som change of Government; and that the King could not stand in the possession of that Power, which hee was formerly intrusted withal: and if I can conceiv, that when swords are drawn, positive Laws are silent, and when those which manage the Supremacie of power are at vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance amongst themselvs, about the fundamentals of their settlement, that then opposite parties in power can act for their own, or the publick safetie, none otherwise, but according to emergencies, and that private men, as good Subjects and Christians ought to <hi>acquiesce,</hi> and make the best use they can of the result of those emergencies;
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:58502:49"/> If (I saie) I am thus principled (and that I ought to bee thus principled in my station, they cannot denie) then it will cleerly follow to my Conscience, that however the change doth fall out, and in whose hand soëver the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er doth remain, I am not to make a new quarrel with them for it; nor to binde over my Conscience, to call them to an account of their former transactions about it, to get it in their hand, nor to refuse them that are in place my concurrence towards the procurement of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-welfare so far, as it may bee atteinable under their Government, by good and lawful waies; which is the cleer case of the present Engagement to my understanding. And if upon the general matter of fact thus stated (which I suppose will not bee denied) and my conscience thus principled (which I suppose will not bee condemned, and I am sure is not convinced, by anie thing which they saie) they tell mee of particular irregularities in former proceedings, and argue from thence as they do; to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that I ought not for the time to com, to concur with the present powers, in the tenor of the Engagement, though I finde in it a cleer dutie, will not I justly (though I might grant them all their premises) denie their conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence? I shall therefore saie, that although they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>competent Judges of matters of fact; and have no right to sentence the present powers to bee without right to their places; yet granting that contrarie to positive Laws, and Contracts setled in former times, between the parties then in power, a change is fallen out in the Government, and the powers, upon the change are now altered; (I saie) granting all this, yet it will not follow, that I am bound in Conscience, either to refuse the taking of the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as it is tendered, or to oppose the present Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which are the two main things they drive at; but you may see how weakly to a judicious Conscience thus principled. Thus then, over and above the grand mistake of the object of the Engagement, you see here again, is a main flaw in the ground of their reasoning, although there had been no such mistake, and although all the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:58502:49"/> of fact which they allege, should bee granted unto them. For let past-matters of fact bee what they will, if it cannot bee made out, that private men, in places of sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, are obliged in Conscience, to judg definitively of the supreme proceedings of their supreme Rulers; then it cannot also bee warrantable, either for them to take those matters of fact, upon which they ground their Arguments, judicially into their consideration, as they do, in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to Conscience; or for mee upon their suggestion to define the same in that same relation, and if this cannot bee don warrantably, either by them, or mee, in respect of things past, but I am bound to look onely to that which is at present, and in time to com, my dutie in my place of Subjection: then all the presupposals upon which they draw inferences, to make good their conclusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, have no argumentative strength at all; but are wholly taken off, and made inconsiderable, as to my Conscience.</p>
            <p>And if it bee objected here, but how can you dispens with you self, from looking judiciously into matters of fact, of a publick nature; Seeing your former oaths and Engagements have obliged you, to have a respect thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and to becom concurrent, to maintein the former set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement? I answer, that the former oaths could not binde mee, to have a respect, or to bee concurrent towards the former settlement, further then my place, and the station of a private man doth allow mee to meddle therein; now that place and station did allow mee, both then, and now, no more but the use of my judgment of discretion, to look upon the changes of publick affairs so, as might bee most advantagious for mee, to manage mine own resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons towards a concurrence, in that which might tend most to the publick good in my waie; therefore I took all the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements as thus meant; nor is it lawful for anie, to ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der anie Engagement unto mee upon anie other terms. Thus then I have still a respect to matters of fact in publick, in my place, by the judgment of discretion, to maintein the settlement which is, as formerly, before the change, I had to maintein the settlement which then was, so long
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:58502:50"/> as it was in beeing: but since, without anie concurrence of mine (who was never called to manage a publick trust) the change is fallen out, by the management of those who were in trust, and a new settlement is erected, and an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement proposed unto mee, to bee true and faithful to the Common-wealth under it; I finde my self bound in Conscience to take that Engagement, without scrupling, or questioning the title of the power, to the place of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie, wherein I finde them, or without calling them, or others to an account, of the causes of the change; I finde these things without my line, and am not warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to meddle definitively with them; and if the <hi>Cheshier</hi> and <hi>Lancashier-</hi>Brethren had seriously resolved upon this matter, I suppose, they needed not to have troubled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selvs, or others with their plea for Non-subscribers, whereof, perhaps it will bee needless, to shew you anie further my sens of it's fundamental weakness. But yet to go one step further, let us suppose, that som of your friends, whom their plea hath mainly prepossessed, will still scruple, and stick at the plausibleness of their funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Argument, as it may bee taken, with som advantage above what the pleaders themselvs have said, from that which I seem to yield: <hi>viz.</hi> that the Government is som part of the object of the Engagement, whence their scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may rise thus: if you grant, that this Government is som part of the object, whereunto wee are to engage, to bee true and faithful; and if it doth appear unto us to bee unjust, unwarranted and oppressive, in regard of the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teinment and continued possession; then wee cannot with a good conscience subscribe to bee true and faithful to it; but you grant that the Government is som part of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, whereunto wee are to engage, to bee true and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and it doth appear to us to bee unjust, unwarranted, and oppressive, &amp;c. therefore wee cannot with a good Conscience subscribe unto it.</p>
            <p>To this there is a twofold Answer. First, I grant not that the Government by it self, and solely considered, is offered to us in the Engagement; but as it is reductive to,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:58502:50"/> and complicated with, the main and direct object of our truth, and faithfulness, which is the Common-wealth of <hi>England:</hi> therefore our Truth and faithfulness is under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood to bee engaged to it, as it is reasonable and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servient to the Common-welfare of the people of this Land. Seeondly, I have shewed, that you as private men and Subjects, are not to take upon you the Judicature of the just, or unjust atteinment, and possession of Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of power in your Superiors: but you are to look onely upon the dutie, which is due to them from you, as you are under them, and they undoubtedly in supreme power; if you trouble your Conscience with more then this; you are out of your line, and in a snare, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ought to free your Conscience from the entanglement thereof: nay, although you should not, nor could not, bee otherwise persuaded, but that those who are in su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme power over you had both gotten, and do hold un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justly their power; yet except you could shew, that the Engagement by obliging you, to bee true and faithful to them, doth intend to engage you to bee so to them, in the waie and cours of their injustice, you have no just ground to scruple the taking of the Engagement; for the pleaders themselvs in page 12. confess, <hi>that men lawfully may promise to bee true and faithful to an unjust partie, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, in that which is just and right;</hi> If then the Engagement doth intend to require nothing of you, but what is just and right, then, although you cannot laie down the scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of their unjust acquisition, and possession of power, yet you may for ought that the pleaders have shewed to the contrarie, take the Engagement; for the pleaders have not at all proved, nor ever attempted, to prove, that the Engagement doth intend, to oblige us to powers which are unjust, in the waie and cours of their unjustice, to bee true and faithful to them; but this they take up <hi>gratis</hi> as a thing granted, though it is not granted, but strongly denied; and so they beg the Question in this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness also, which is the fundamental weakness of their plea; as for mine own part, I am cleer in that which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:58502:51"/> hath been said, concerning the object of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, in the sens which the Act explain's it, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides, if wee look upon the Act, by which the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is injoined to bee taken, wee shall finde in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face thereof the intent for which it is to bee taken, to bee none other but to prevent conspiracies, tumults, and wars against the present settlement, which is a thing absolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly just and lawful, to bee required of Subjects by their Magistrates, and to bee promised by Subjects unto their Magistrates. If then this is the professed and declared purpose of the Engagement, although it should bee never so manifest, that they who are in places of power had gotten, and hold their places unjustly; yet if the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement doth oblige these that take it, to nothing but what is just, by the pleader's own confession it may bee taken: therefore I suppose it is abundantly made out, that it obligeth the takers to nothing, but what is just, both in respect of the object, whereunto it engageth us, and in respect of the intent and purpose, for which it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joined to bee taken.</p>
            <p>The last matter of proof which they insist upon, from page 43. till 57. is a plausible allegation of the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictoriness of former oaths, to the object of the present Engagement, as they deliver it, and of these oaths in force, to oblige to this present time. To make these oaths seem contradictorie to the Engagement, having alleged the words of them which mention an obligation to the King, and kinglie Government, and to the privileges of Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they oppose a Common-wealth-State, and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, without a King and Hous of Lords, and a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment solely, and onely established in a partie of the Hous of Commons, and then to make them seem still obligatorie; they allege first, the provision of Duration made by the oaths themselvs. Secondly, that the waies and means by which oaths are repealable, and may bee annulled are not appliable to these; Thirdly, that the things sworn to, remain still lawful, and possible, and therefore the oaths still binding.</p>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:58502:51"/>
            <p> To these allegations, this is truly, advisedly, without respect of persons, and partial interests to bee said (as in page 46. they desire such as <hi>are not of a reprobate minde to judg,)</hi> that if the object which they put upon the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, were such as they make it, then indeed there could bee no reconciling of these oaths with this Engagement; but becaus it is evident, that the object of the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is not what they saie it is, but what wee have prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it to bee, <hi>viz, the Common-welfare, and Freedom of the People of the Land, in their National association;</hi> therefore there is no such contradiction, between the Engagement and the former oaths, as they represent: the difference is onely, that the former Engagements aiming at the same thing, which this doth aim at <hi>(viz.</hi> the Common-wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of the people of the Land,) they mention the means then in beeing, by which that aim was to bee prosecuted by all men, in their several places, and so oblige them to make use of them, and to uphold them, so long as it should bee possible, and lawful for them so to do; but this later En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement doth mention the abolition, or non-existence of those means, and yet doth oblige to the full prosecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the same aim; which to my understanding doth cleerly take away the contradiction: for I saie, except there bee shewed an opposition, in the intents and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poses of the former and later Engagements, there is no contradiction; but this cannot bee shewed, if the object of the later Engagement bee truly stated: for if it could not bee the meaning of the Laws, by which the former En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements were established, to intend mainly anie other thing by those oaths, then that the Common-welfare of the people of the Land should bee upheld, by the means and waies mentioned therein; then there can bee no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction between them and this Engagement, which doth in express terms intend nothing els. But I suppose it is cleer to all, that the meaning of the Laws, by which these oaths were established, was none other. Therefore there can bee no contradiction between them and this Engagement; for although they mention not the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:58502:52"/> and the Rights annexed to the Imperial Crown, &amp;c. and that no fear, nor terror, nor anie earthlie thing shall make us alter this resolution; this is certainly to bee under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood, with this supposal, that the things remaining so as they are, wee shall bee so towards them as wee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise; that is, wee shall endevor to maintein them, and that no fear nor danger shall caus us to alter that resolution; but in case the King's Autoritie should ceas to bee, or ceas to bee just, or in case that state of Parlament-Privileges should com to bee utterly abolished, and the rights annexed to the Imperial Crown made wholly void, then I suppose it is not understood, that I am (notwithstanding such emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies) obliged to maintein them, and that without anie respect to Common welfare, and without anie respect to the lawfulness and possibilitie of the prosecution thereof, in my place and calling; and if it bee considered, that in extraordinarie emergencies in a state, no positive Consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, Laws, and rights are able to keep up the establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment setled upon them; but that in such cases, all men must flie to the fundamentals of the universal law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to do that, which by it's tenor is most warrantable, and expedient for common safetie, and consequently, that in such cases, all circumstances of former Engagements be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing altered, nothing but the main end, and the main Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of common safetie and societie, will hold out, and bee obliging: if (I saie) this bee considered in these, and then in <hi>Hypothesi</hi> applied to our present affairs, and the changes under which God hath brought us, I conceiv it will bee evident enough to perceiv, that the oaths which formerly (as matters then stood between us, as private men, and our Superiors) were lawful, are not now at all in force, as matters now stand between us, as private men, and the superior powers which are over us; if therefore the Brethren that make this plea, for the continued force of former oaths, in respect of circumstantials, to bee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging to the consciences of private men, would have dealt with us convincingly, and strongly, they should have made it out unto us, either in <hi>thesi,</hi> that notwithstanding all
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:58502:52"/> possible emergencies, such oaths, are still in all respects to bee obliging; or in <hi>Hypothesi,</hi> that now to us, in this change of State-affairs no such emergencies are fallen out, as are valid, to take off the former circumstantial parts of our obligation; but becaus I finde no such thing proved, nor attempted to bee proved, therefore their plea to mee is weak in this respect also.</p>
            <p>These are all the pillars upon which that building of theirs doth stand, which having so weak and sandie foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, as I have discovered them to have, will fall to the ground, in the thoughts of such, as without prejudice will search into these matters. The particulars need not further to bee insisted upon: becaus they are matters of fact, and of positive Law, which I make not my work to dive into, so as to build anie conscientious judgment of doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful matters thereupon, in these emergencies to steer my cours by. And becaus the chief things therein considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which relate unto Conscience, are either fully resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in other Treatises, and particularly in the <hi>Memoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dums</hi> of the conferences, which lately I sent unto you; or will receiv a more particular cleering from som papers, which I have in a readiness, to bee made communicable unto you, and others, who stagger in their waie, and stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at these stumbling stones, I shall continue to praie unto the Lord, that wee may all bee more and more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned, and directed to impart the light, which wee have received in the spirit of meekness, and love one to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, without anie other end or design, then our mutual edification in Righteousness, to the glorie of our God in Jesus Chrtst, in whom I am truly for the Gospel of Peace sake</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your unfeignedly affectionate<lb/> Brother and servant</hi>
                  <lb/> JOHN DURIE.</signed>
               <lb/>
               <dateline>St <hi>James's</hi> this<lb/>
                  <date>20. <hi>Sept.</hi> 1650.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:58502:53"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthie Sir!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Received the books you sent, and return you manie thanks; I must needs acknowledg, that I cannot sufficiently express, how much I am obliged unto you, that are pleased to shew so great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect to mee, a stranger to you, and such as by no interest of desert, can claim the least respect from you. <hi>Give mee leav to provoke you to pursue your intentions, of giving an answer to</hi> Lancashier-<hi>Ministers, and not to bee wearie of the work you have begun, in seeking to give satisfaction to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences of such, as are truly tender, and are kept off from engaging, by nothing, but onely by fear of offending God; what you have already don in these two last pieces, I doubt not but will give eas to manie that have been pinch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and what you intend to do, will give further help in this kinde.</hi> If your pains should not have that success, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect with men, as they deserv; yet that God who seeth the since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of your heart, and the integritie of your intentions, will not let you go unrewarded; but when that promiss of blessedness pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced to Peace-makers com's to bee fulfilled, you shall then reap the full fruit of all your labors. Our good God assist you, and give you happie success in all your undertakings, and endevors, to this end and purpose; to his mercie I resign you, and rest</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your most obliged friend and faithful Brother in Christ.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>The 19<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of</hi> Octob: 1650.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The greater faults.</head>
               <p>PAge 17. line ult. for ym read my, page 28. l. 17. for follow, r. follow it. p. 41. l. 20. f. in these, r. <hi>in Thesi.</hi> p. 54. l. 20, 21. r. Rule is given. p. 85. l, 27. f. grant that the, r. grant the, p. 59. l. 9. f. will make, r. will not make, p. 81. l. 23, 24. r. right use of, p. 90. l. 7. f. arrest, r. wrest.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The lesser.</head>
               <p>In the title for occasionably, read occasionally, p. 11. l. 35. f. implore, r. implie, p. 22. l. 28. f. prudentially, r. providentially, p. 46. l. 11. f. step. r. stop, p. 66. l. 5. f. commons, r. common, p. 93. l. 10. f. erection, r. election.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>